<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<addictedtor>
  <!-- Table graph -->
    <graph>
        <id>1</id>
        <titre>Kernel density estimator in R²&lt;br&gt; Perspective plot and contour plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Estimateur à noyau de la densité dans R² &lt;br&gt;Graphique 3D et lignes de niveaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>That plot displays the estimation of the density of a 2d sample.
The density itself is computed with &lt;tt&gt;kde2d&lt;/tt&gt; in the package &lt;tt&gt;MASS&lt;/tt&gt; (bundle VR).
On the left side, there is the perspective plot of the density, obtained by &lt;tt&gt;persp&lt;/tt&gt;. 
On the right side, there is the contour plot (&lt;tt&gt;contour&lt;/tt&gt;). Colours are generated by &lt;tt&gt;topo.colors&lt;/tt&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphique présente l'estimation de la densité d'un échantillon bivarié par la méthode des noyaux. Le calcul de la densité est effectué par la fonction &lt;tt&gt;kde2d&lt;/tt&gt;. &lt;br&gt;A gauche, un graphique en perspective (3D) obtenu par &lt;tt&gt;persp&lt;/tt&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
A droite, les lignes de niveaux obtenues par &lt;tt&gt;contour&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt; Les couleurs sont choisies en utilisant la fonction &lt;tt&gt;topo.colors&lt;/tt&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>1.9123128629715</notemoy>
        <nbNote>6546</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>2</id>
        <titre>Winner of the R Homepage&lt;br&gt;graphics competition 2004</titre>
        <titre_fr>Vainqueur de la R homepage graphics competition 2004</titre_fr>
        <comments>This is a complex &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=layout.html&amp;alias=layout&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/a&gt; arrangement illustrating how several graph can be put together as the user wants. &lt;br/&gt;
The graph represents principal component analysis (PCA). The main figure is the samples projection on the 1-3 plan, samples are coloured to follow clustering results and their size indicates the quality of the projection (given by the relative contributions : COS2). &lt;br/&gt;
Then on the left can be seen a representation of the variables on the correlation circle. A barplot shows the inertia of each axe.&lt;br/&gt;
The bottom-left panel shows a clustering tree and illustrates the number of samples in each group obtained by a cut of the tree.&lt;br/&gt;
Last, distribution of the margin (axes 1 and 3) are represented by a wise combination of kernel density estimator and boxplot.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Voici un arrangement &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=layout.html&amp;alias=layout&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/a&gt; complexe,
qui illustre pleinement comment différents graphiques peuvent être combinés tel que l'utilisateur le souhaite. &lt;br/&gt;
Ce graphique présente l'analyse en composante principale (ACP). La figure principale 
est le plan 1-3 des individus. La couleur de représentation des individus correspond à leur groupe d'appartenance, et leur taille varie selon la qualité de représentation sur le plan factoriel 1-3 (cette qualité étant donnée par les contributions relatives : COS2)&lt;br/&gt;
A coté, le cercle des corrélation des variables (toujours sur le plan 1-3) accompagné d'un diagramme en baton illustrant les inerties de chaque axe. &lt;br/&gt;
La partie en bas à gauche montre un arbre de classification coupé à la hauteur 48 pour donner 4 groupes. La répartition des individus dans ces 4 groupes est donnée par un autre diagramme en baton à coté de l'arbre. &lt;br/&gt;
Enfin, la distribution marginale des composantes principales 1 et 3 est illustrée au moyen d'une combinaison astucieuse de boxplot et d'estimateur de la densité par la méthode des noyaux.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>76.550724637681</notemoy>
        <nbNote>207</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>31</id>
        <titre>Tukey's Hanging&lt;br&gt;Rootogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Rootogram de Tukey</titre_fr>
        <comments>Discrete frequency distributions are often graphed as histograms, with a theoretical fitted distribution superimposed. It is hard to compare the observed and fitted frequencies visually, because (a) we must assess deviations against a curvilinear relation, and (b)  the largest frequencies dominate the display. 

The hanging rootogram (Tukey, 1977) solves these problems by (a) shifting the histogram bars to coincide with the fitted curve, so
that deviations may be judged by deviations from a horizontal line, and (b) plotting on a square-root scale, so that smaller frequencies are emphasized. Featured example shows more clearly that the observed frequencies differ systematically from those predicted under a Poisson model. 
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les distributions de probabilité discrètes sont (trop) souvent présentées sous forme d'histogramme, avec une distribution théorique superposée. Il est difficile de comparer visuellement les probabilités ajustées et observées car : &lt;br&gt;
- il faut visualiser les déviations par rapport à une relation curvilinéaire&lt;br&gt;
- les fréquences les plus probables dominent le graphique.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

Le rootogram de Tukey (1977) résouds ces problèmes en  : &lt;br&gt;
- déplacant l'histogramme de façon à faire coincider la courbe ajustée, les déviations peuvent alors être appréciées par une ligne horizontale. &lt;br&gt;
- représentant sur une échelle en racine carrée, ainsi les petites probabilités sont mises en valeur.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

L'exemple montre clairement que les probabilités observées diffèrent systématiquement des probabilités prédites sous un modèle de Poisson.
</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>54.6</notemoy>
        <nbNote>30</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>3</id>
        <titre>Simple Use of Color In a Plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Utilisation de la couleur dans un graphique</titre_fr>
        <comments>Here is some code which illustrates some of the differences between
R and S graphics capabilities.  Note that colors are generally specified
by a character string name (taken from the X11 rgb.txt file) and that line
textures are given similarly.	 The parameter  &lt;tt&gt;bg&lt;/tt&gt; sets the background
parameter for the plot and there is also an &lt;tt&gt;fg&lt;/tt&gt; parameter which sets
the foreground color.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Le code présenté illustre quelques différences entre les possibilités graphiques de R et S.
On peut noter que les couleurs sont généralement spécifiées par une chaine de caractères (voir le fichier rgb.txt de X11) et que les textures de ligne sont données de la même façon.
&lt;br&gt;Le paramètre &lt;tt&gt;bg&lt;/tt&gt; fixe la couleur de fond du graphique. Il existe aussi un paramètre &lt;tt&gt;fg&lt;/tt&gt; pour la couleur de premier plan, comme la couleur par défaut du texte.</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>35.094339622642</notemoy>
        <nbNote>53</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>4</id>
        <titre>Pie chart&lt;br&gt;A sample color wheel</titre>
        <titre_fr>Camembert&lt;br&gt;Une simple roue colorée</titre_fr>
        <comments>A little color wheel.	 This code just plots equally spaced hues in
a pie chart.	If you have a cheap SVGA monitor (like me) you will
probably find that numerically equispaced does not mean visually
equispaced.  On my display at home, these colors tend to cluster at
the RGB primaries.  On the other hand on the SGI Indy at work the
effect is near perfect.

</comments>
        <comments_fr>Une simple roue colorée. Ce code dessine simplement des tonalités équiréparties sur un camembert. </comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>39.684931506849</notemoy>
        <nbNote>73</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>5</id>
        <titre>Pie chart&lt;br&gt;January pie sales</titre>
        <titre_fr>Camembert&lt;br&gt; Ventes de janvier</titre_fr>
        <comments>We have already confessed to having these.  This is just showing off X11
color names (and the example (from the postscript manual) is pretty &quot;cute&quot;.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>On peut voir ici le nom des couleurs X11. L'exemple issu du manuel poscript est assez joli.</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>1.8144830160514</notemoy>
        <nbNote>2679</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>6</id>
        <titre>Notched boxplots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Boxplots / Boites à moustaches</titre_fr>
        <comments>Boxplots:  I couldn't resist the capability for filling the &quot;box&quot;.
The use of color seems like a useful addition, it focuses attention
on the central bulk of the data.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Voici les boxplots (boites à moustaches). Impossible de résister à la tentation de remplir la boite. L'utilisation de la couleur est un apport utile, cela attire l'attention sur la masse centrale des données.</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>0.83150470219441</notemoy>
        <nbNote>2552</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>7</id>
        <titre>Distance Between Brownian Motions</titre>
        <titre_fr>Distance entre mouvements Brownien</titre_fr>
        <comments>An example showing how to fill between curves.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphique montre la possibilité de remplir un espace entre deux courbes à l'aide de la fonction &lt;tt&gt;polygon&lt;/tt&gt;</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>23.478991596636</notemoy>
        <nbNote>119</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>8</id>
        <titre>The level of interest in R</titre>
        <titre_fr>Evolution de l'intérêt pour R</titre_fr>
        <comments>Colored plot margins, axis labels and titles.	 You do need to be
careful with these kinds of effects.	It's easy to go completely
over the top and you can end up with your lunch all over the keyboard.
On the other hand, my market research clients love it.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Comment ajouter de la couleur sur le graphique, dans les marges, le titre et les axes. Faites attention avec ces effets. Il est facile de finir avec votre sandwich sur le clavier à peaufinner votre graphique. Cependant, mes clienst adorent.</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>65.176470588235</notemoy>
        <nbNote>17</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>9</id>
        <titre>A filled histogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Un histogramme rempli</titre_fr>
        <comments>A filled histogram, showing how to change the font used for the
main title without changing the other annotation.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Un simple histogramme, illustrant comment changer la police utilisée pour le titre principal sans affecter les autres annotations</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>69.341880341878</notemoy>
        <nbNote>117</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>10</id>
        <titre>Edgar Anderson's Iris Data&lt;br&gt;pairs plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique matriciel. données iris.</titre_fr>
        <comments>A scatterplot matrix.&lt;br&gt;
The good old Iris data (yet again)
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Une matrice de nuages de points sur les bonnes vieilles données iris d'Edgar Anderson.</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>39.375</notemoy>
        <nbNote>40</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>11</id>
        <titre>A Topographic Map of Maunga Whau&lt;br&gt;contour plotting</titre>
        <titre_fr>Carte topographique du Maunga Whau. Lignes de niveaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>Contour plotting&lt;br&gt;
This produces a topographic map of one of Auckland's many volcanic &quot;peaks&quot;.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Lignes de niveaux. Affiche une carte topographique du Maunga Whau, un des nombreux volcans de la région d'Auckland (la maison de R).</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>53.125</notemoy>
        <nbNote>8</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>12</id>
        <titre>Conditionning plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique conditionnel</titre_fr>
        <comments>Conditioning plots</comments>
        <comments_fr>graphique conditionnel</comments_fr>
        <demo>graphics</demo>
        <notemoy>0.56769596199524</notemoy>
        <nbNote>421</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>13</id>
        <titre>Hershey Vector Fonts&lt;br&gt;Sample 'a'</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polices vectoriells Hershey. Lettre 'a'</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hershey Vector Fonts&lt;br&gt;Sample 'a' for each available font</comments>
        <comments_fr>Polices vectoriells Hershey. Lettre 'a' pour chaque police disponible</comments_fr>
        <demo>Hershey</demo>
        <notemoy>32.5</notemoy>
        <nbNote>10</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>14</id>
        <titre>Hershey Vector Fonts &lt;br&gt;Symbol (incl. Greek) Escape Sequences</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt; Séquences d'échappement</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hershey Vector Fonts&lt;br&gt;Symbol (incl. Greek) Escape Sequences</comments>
        <comments_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt; Séquences d'échappement grecques.</comments_fr>
        <demo>Hershey</demo>
        <notemoy>0.1429750361048</notemoy>
        <nbNote>4847</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>15</id>
        <titre>Hershey Vector Fonts&lt;br&gt;ISO Latin-1 Escape Sequences</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Séquences d'échappement ISO Latin-1</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hershey Vector Fonts&lt;br&gt;ISO Latin-1 Escape Sequences</comments>
        <comments_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Séquences d'échappement ISO Latin-1</comments_fr>
        <demo>Hershey</demo>
        <notemoy>11.111111111111</notemoy>
        <nbNote>9</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>16</id>
        <titre>Hershey Vector Fonts&lt;br&gt;Special Escape Sequences</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Séquences d'échappement spéciales</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hershey Vector Fonts&lt;br&gt;Special Escape Sequences</comments>
        <comments_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Séquences d'échappement spéciales</comments_fr>
        <demo>Hershey</demo>
        <notemoy>19</notemoy>
        <nbNote>5</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>17</id>
        <titre>Hershey Vector Fonts &lt;br&gt;Cyrillic Octal Codes</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Codes octaux pour le cyrillique</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hershey Vector Fonts &lt;br&gt;Cyrillic Octal Codes</comments>
        <comments_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Codes octaux pour le cyrillique</comments_fr>
        <demo>Hershey</demo>
        <notemoy>35.714285714286</notemoy>
        <nbNote>7</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>18</id>
        <titre>Hershey Vector Fonts &lt;br&gt;More Special Escape Sequences</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;D'autres séquences d'échappement</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hershey Vector Fonts &lt;br&gt;More Special Escape Sequences</comments>
        <comments_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;D'autres séquences d'échappement</comments_fr>
        <demo>Hershey</demo>
        <notemoy>48.666666666667</notemoy>
        <nbNote>3</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>19</id>
        <titre>Hershey Vector Fonts &lt;br&gt;More Special Escape Sequences (2)</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Encore d'autres séquences d'échappement</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hershey Vector Fonts &lt;br&gt;More Special Escape Sequences (2)</comments>
        <comments_fr>Polices vectorielles Hershey. &lt;br&gt;Encore d'autres séquences d'échappement</comments_fr>
        <demo>Hershey</demo>
        <notemoy>0.33333333333333</notemoy>
        <nbNote>3</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>20</id>
        <titre>contour plot &lt;br&gt;Maunga Whau Volcano</titre>
        <titre_fr>Volcan de Maunga Whau. &lt;br&gt;Lignes de niveaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>Maunga Whau Volcano. &lt;br&gt;Contour plot using heat colors.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Volcan de Maunga Whau. Lignes de niveaux utilisant le jeu de couleurs heat.</comments_fr>
        <demo>image</demo>
        <notemoy>71.953875000001</notemoy>
        <nbNote>80</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>21</id>
        <titre>contour plot &lt;br&gt;Maunga Whau Volcano</titre>
        <titre_fr>Volcan Maunga Whau &lt;br&gt; Lignes de niveaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>Maunga Whau Volcano. &lt;br&gt;Contour plot using gray scales.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Volcan de Maunga Whau. Lignes de niveaux (contour) utilisant une échelle de gris</comments_fr>
        <demo>image</demo>
        <notemoy>58.875</notemoy>
        <nbNote>8</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>22</id>
        <titre>contour plot &lt;br&gt;Maunga Whau Volcano</titre>
        <titre_fr>Volcan Maunga Whau &lt;br&gt; Lignes de niveaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>Maunga Whau Volcano. &lt;br&gt;Contour plot using heat colors.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Lignes de niveaux (contour) utilisant le jeu de couleurs heat sur les données du volcan Maunga Whau, volcan de la région d'Auckland</comments_fr>
        <demo>image</demo>
        <notemoy>63.92857142857</notemoy>
        <nbNote>28</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>23</id>
        <titre>Perspective plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphique en perspective (3D)</titre_fr>
        <comments>The Obligatory Mathematical surface : Rotated sinc function.&lt;br&gt;
The right plot shows a nice shade effect controlled by the parameters of &lt;tt&gt;persp&lt;/tt&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>La surface mathématique obligatoire : sinc . &lt;br&gt;
Le graphique de droite montre un effet d'ombre agréable controlé par les paramètres de la fonction &lt;tt&gt;persp&lt;/tt&gt;</comments_fr>
        <demo>persp</demo>
        <notemoy>23.808764940234</notemoy>
        <nbNote>251</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>24</id>
        <titre>Perspective plot.&lt;br&gt;Simple DEM model</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphique en perspective.</titre_fr>
        <comments>Visualizing a simple DEM model. Again the Maunga Whau Volcano.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Visualisation d'un simple modèle DEM. Les données du volcan Maunga Whau sont encore utilisées.</comments_fr>
        <demo>persp</demo>
        <notemoy>48.88</notemoy>
        <nbNote>25</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>25</id>
        <titre>Perspective plot.&lt;br&gt;Less simple DEM model</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graph en persperctive. Maunga Whau</titre_fr>
        <comments>The Maunga Whau Volcano. We border the surface, to make it more &quot;slice like&quot;
and color the top and sides of the surface differently. Top is in 
&lt;tt&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00CD00&quot;&gt;green3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, background is in
&lt;tt&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#add8e6&quot;&gt;lightblue&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;
 and sides are in 
&lt;tt&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#BEBEBE&quot;&gt;gray&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; (R color names).
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Le volcan Maunga Whau. Nous avons ici entouré la surface, de facon à ressembler à une tranche. Les couleurs utilisés pour le dessus et le bord sont différentes. La couleur pour le dessus est &lt;tt&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00CD00&quot;&gt;green3&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, la couleur de fond est &lt;tt&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#add8e6&quot;&gt;lightblue&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; et les bords sont en &lt;tt&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#BEBEBE&quot;&gt;gray&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; (ce sont le nom R des couleurs)</comments_fr>
        <demo>persp</demo>
        <notemoy>71.451612903225</notemoy>
        <nbNote>31</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>26</id>
        <titre>Perspective plot&lt;br&gt;Maunga Whau, One of 50 Volcanoes in the Auckland Region</titre>
        <comments>Perspective plot&lt;br&gt;Maunga Whau, One of 50 Volcanoes in the Auckland Region</comments>
        <demo>persp</demo>
        <notemoy>47.088235294117</notemoy>
        <nbNote>34</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>27</id>
        <titre>An other perspective plot of the Maunga Whau</titre>
        <comments>An other perspective plot of the Maunga Whau with a nice set of colors.</comments>
        <demo>persp</demo>
        <notemoy>72.014510729613</notemoy>
        <nbNote>233</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>28</id>
        <titre>plotmath&lt;br&gt;mathematical annontations</titre>
        <comments>plotmath, mathematical annontations in graphics</comments>
        <demo>plotmath</demo>
        <notemoy>8.687999999999</notemoy>
        <nbNote>125</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>29</id>
        <titre>Backward selection in arima models</titre>
        <titre_fr>Sélection descendante pour modèles arima</titre_fr>
        <comments>That plot shows the step of selection of coefficients in an ARMA(7,3) model. Each row of the center graph correspond to a step of the backward selection. Each coefficient is represented both by its value and a color (the rainbow under the graph allow user to get the value of the coefficient). The significance of those coefficients is tested by a t test represented by the triangles at the bottom right of each case. &lt;br&gt;
On the left side of the graph, the aic is represented for each step.&lt;br&gt;
On the right side, acf, pacf and qqnorm of the residuals of the selected model
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphique présente les différentes étapes de sélection des coefficients d'un modèle ARMA(7,3). Chaque ligne du graph corresppond à une étape de la sélection descendante. Chaque coefficient est représenté à la fois par sa valeur et la couleur de sa case (le dégradé sous le graphe permet de retrouver la valeur). La significativité de ces coefficients est testé à la student. Les p-values de ces tests sont représentées en bas à droite de chaque case.&lt;br&gt; 
A gauche, on peut voir l'évolution du critère AIC.&lt;br&gt;
A droite, on trouve autocorrélations, autocorrélations partielles et diagramme quantiles-quantiles des résidus du modèle finalement sélectionné. </comments_fr>
        <notemoy>67.684210526314</notemoy>
        <nbNote>76</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>30</id>
        <titre>Kernel density estimator&lt;br&gt;Illustration of the kernels</titre>
        <titre_fr>estimation à noyaux de la densité. Illustration des noyaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>That graph nicely shows the construction of the kernel density estimator (R function 
&lt;tt&gt;density&lt;/tt&gt; on a sample of size 5. Note that this is just illustrative, 5 points is really small to consider an estimation of the density. The colors of the components to the density are chosen by the package &lt;tt&gt;RColorBrewer&lt;/tt&gt; available on CRAN.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphe montre la construction d'un estimateur à noyaux de la densité sur un échantillon de taille 5 (même s'il n'est pas correct d'utiliser une telle méthode sur 5 données). Les couleurs des différents noyaux sont choisies à l'aide du package RColorBrewer disponible sur CRAN.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>23.357043478261</notemoy>
        <nbNote>115</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>32</id>
        <titre>Fourfold Display</titre>
        <comments>The fourfold display depicts frequencies by quarter circles, whose radius is proportional to `\sqrt{n_{ij}}` , so the area is proportional to the cell count . The cell frequencies
are usually scaled to equate the marginal totals, and so that the ratio of diagonally opposite segments depicts the odds ratio.
Confidence rings for the observed odd ratio allow a visual test of the
hypothesis `H_0: \theta=1`  corresponding to no association. They have the property that the rings for adjacent quadrants overlap iff the observed counts are consistent with the null hypothesis.
</comments>
        <notemoy>9.7954545454554</notemoy>
        <nbNote>44</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>33</id>
        <titre>Agreement plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Agreement plot</titre_fr>
        <comments>Representation of a $k*k$ confusion matrix, where the observed and expected diagonal elements are represented by superposed black and white rectangles, respectively.

Agreement chart allows to quickly see where two judges do disagree.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Représentation d'une matrice $k*k$ de confusion, où les valeurs observées et prédites de la diagonale sont représentées par des rectangles blancs et noirs superposés.
Les graphiques d'agrément permettent aussi de voir rapidement où deux juges sont en désaccord.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>80.418604651164</notemoy>
        <nbNote>43</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>34</id>
        <titre>Ternary Plot</titre>
        <comments>Graphs for a dataframe with 3 columns of positive or null values
     &lt;tt&gt;triangle.plot&lt;/tt&gt; is a scatterplot
     &lt;tt&gt;triangle.biplot&lt;/tt&gt; is a paired scatterplots</comments>
        <notemoy>73.292682926828</notemoy>
        <nbNote>82</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>35</id>
        <titre>Parallel plot</titre>
        <notemoy>45.727272727274</notemoy>
        <nbNote>11</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>36</id>
        <titre>Mosaic plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Mosaique</titre_fr>
        <comments> Mosaicplot graph represents a contingency table, each cell corresponding to a piece of the plot, which size is proportional to cell entry.

Extended mosaic displays show the standardized residuals of a
     loglinear model of the counts from by the color and outline of the
     mosaic's tiles.  (Standardized residuals are often referred to a
     standard normal distribution.)  Negative residuals are drawn in
     shaded of red and with broken outlines; positive ones are drawn in
     blue with solid outlines.

Thus, mosaicplot are perfect to visualize associations within a table and to detect cells which create dependancies.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les mosaiques (mosaicplot) représentent une table de contingence, chaque cellule correspondant à une partie du graphique, de taille proportionnelle à la donnée de la cellule.&lt;br&gt;

Une mosaique étendue montre les résidus standardisés d'un modèle loglinéaire des comptes à travers les couleurs et le type des lignes utilisées. Les résidus standardisés sont souvent considérés comme une référence à une distribution normale standard. Les résidus négatifs sont dessinnés en pointillés et en rouge. Les résidus positifs sont dessinnés en bleu avec des traits pleins.&lt;br&gt;

Ainsi, les mosaiques sont parfaites pour visualiser les associations d'une table et pour détecter les cellules avec haute dépendance.

</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>0.21284439270466</notemoy>
        <nbNote>10308</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>37</id>
        <titre>Parallel plot 2</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique parrallèle</titre_fr>
        <comments>An other parallel plot with the famous iris data.</comments>
        <comments_fr>graphique en parrallèle sur le jeu de données iris</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>64.615384615385</notemoy>
        <nbNote>13</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>38</id>
        <titre>Hexagon Binning&lt;br&gt;Matrix</titre>
        <titre_fr>Matrice hexbin</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hexagon binning is a form of bivariate histogram useful for visualizing
the structure in datasets with large $n$. The underlying concept of
hexagon binning is extremely simple;

&lt;br&gt;-the $xy$ plane over the set (range($x$), range($y$)) is tessellated
by a regular grid of hexagons.

&lt;br&gt;- the counts of points falling in each hexagon are counted and
stored in a data structure

&lt;br&gt;- the hexagons with count $ &gt; 0$ are plotted using a color ramp or
varying the radius of the hexagon in proportion to the counts.

The algorithm is extremely fast and effective for displaying the
structure of datasets with $n \ge 10^6$.
If the size of the grid and the cuts in the color ramp are chosen in a
clever fashion than the structure inherent in the data should emerge
in the binned plots. The same caveats apply to hexagon binning as
apply to histograms and care should be exercised in choosing the
binning parameters.

The hexbin library is a set of function for creating and plotting
hexagon bins. The library extends the basic hexagon binning ideas with
several functions for doing bivariate smoothing, finding an
approximate bivariate median, and looking at the difference between
two sets of bins on the same scale. The basic functions can be
incorporated into many types of plots.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>hexbin est une forme d'histogramme 2D utile pour la visualisation d'importants jeux de données. Le concept sous-jacent de hexbin est extrêmement simple. &lt;br&gt;

- le plan (x,y) est découpé par une grille régulière hexagonale.&lt;br&gt;
- le nombre de points dans chaque hexagone est comptabilisé et enregistré dans une structure de données.&lt;br&gt;
- les hexagones au comptes positifs sont tracés en utilisant une échelle de couleur et un rayon de l'hexagone proportionnel au compte.&lt;br&gt;

L'algorithme utilisé est extrêmement rapide et efficace pour présenter des jeux de données avec plus de 10 000 individus. La taille de la grille et les points de coupure sont judicieusement choisis de façon à faire apparaitre dans les hexagones la structure sous-jacente des données. Le même type de soin est demandé pour juger des paramètres d'ajustement que dans le cadre de l'histogramme.&lt;br&gt;

Le package hexbin (de Bioconductor) est un ensemble de fonctions pour créer et tracer des graphiques hexagonaux. Le package étends les idées traditionnelles hexbin avec quelques fonctions pour faire du lissage bidimensionnel, trouver une médiane bidimensionnelle approximative, et apprécier la différence entre deux jeux de données sur la même grille. Ces fonctions peuvent être incorporées dans de nommbreux graphiques

</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>50.948275862069</notemoy>
        <nbNote>58</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>39</id>
        <titre>Conditionning plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique conditionnel</titre_fr>
        <comments>Conditionning plot</comments>
        <comments_fr>graphique conditionnel</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>66.400000000001</notemoy>
        <nbNote>15</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>40</id>
        <titre>wireframe</titre>
        <titre_fr>wireframe</titre_fr>
        <comments>3D wireframe for surfaces</comments>
        <comments_fr>représentation de surfaces en 3D avec lattice</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>4.1872586872588</notemoy>
        <nbNote>518</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>41</id>
        <titre>Scatter plot 3D</titre>
        <titre_fr>nuage de points en 3D</titre_fr>
        <comments>Iris data in 3 dimensions</comments>
        <comments_fr>données d'iris en trois dimensions</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>52.471698113208</notemoy>
        <nbNote>53</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>42</id>
        <titre>Normal density surface</titre>
        <titre_fr>Surface de densité gaussienne</titre_fr>
        <comments>Normal density surface. Beside doing a 3D graph, we see here how mathematical annotations car be added in a graph.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Surface de densité gaussienne. en plus du graphique en 3D, ce graphique montre comment intégrer des formules mathématiques poussées à l'intérieur d'un graph.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>1.9724524076142</notemoy>
        <nbNote>4465</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>43</id>
        <titre>Violin plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Violon plot</titre_fr>
        <comments>Violin plot are similar to boxplot except that they show the density of the data, estimated by kernel method.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les violon plot sont similaires aux boites à moustaches. Ils montrent la densité des données, telle qu'elle est estimée par la méthode des noyaux</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>51.764705882351</notemoy>
        <nbNote>119</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>44</id>
        <titre>Scatter plot 3D</titre>
        <titre_fr>nuage de points en 3 dimension</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plots a three dimensional (3D) point cloud</comments>
        <comments_fr>Trace un nuage de points tridimensionnel</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>13.693055555558</notemoy>
        <nbNote>288</nbNote>
        <example>scatterplot3d</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>45</id>
        <titre>Boxplots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Boxplots (boites à moustaches)</titre_fr>
        <comments>Nice coloured boxplots. See how the legend is put on the upper-left corner thanks to 
gplots::&lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=gplots&amp;fun=smartlegend.html&amp;alias=smartlegend&quot;&gt;smartlegend&lt;/a&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Boites à moustaches colorées. Notons comment la légende est calée dans le coin Nord-Ouest grace à la fonction gplots::&lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=gplots&amp;fun=smartlegend.html&amp;alias=smartlegend&quot;&gt;smartlegend&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>69.322916666667</notemoy>
        <nbNote>48</nbNote>
        <example>boxplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>46</id>
        <titre>Double coplot</titre>
        <comments>A double conditioning plot using the crabs dataset in MASS. This plot shows
frontal lobe lengths against rear widths conditioned by colour variation and
by sex for the crab leptograpsus variegatus.  Cubic smoothing splines have
been fit to the data in each panel.
</comments>
        <notemoy>63.608695652173</notemoy>
        <nbNote>23</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>47</id>
        <titre>Andrew curves</titre>
        <titre_fr>courbe d'Andrew</titre_fr>
        <comments>Here is an example of the Andrew curve on iris data</comments>
        <comments_fr>Voici un exemple de courbe d'Andrew sur les bien connues données d'iris</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>70.224999999999</notemoy>
        <nbNote>40</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>48</id>
        <titre>Lattice graphic</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique lattice</titre_fr>
        <comments>An example lattice graph illustrating how to control separate elements in a point and line plot in order to get a good looking black and white graph. &lt;br&gt;
Note : that graph is also a demonstration of the power of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/posting-guide.html&quot;&gt;R-help&lt;/a&gt; system, check 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tolstoy.newcastle.edu.au/R/help/05/04/3158.html&quot;&gt;that thread&lt;/a&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Simple exemple de graphique lattice montrant comment controler séparement les éléments d'un graphique avec lignes et points afin d'obtenir un graphique en noir et blanc agréable à regarder.&lt;br&gt;
Note : ce graph est également une illustration de la puissance du système 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/posting-guide.html&quot;&gt;R-help&lt;/a&gt;, regarder ce  
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tolstoy.newcastle.edu.au/R/help/05/04/3158.html&quot;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>36</notemoy>
        <nbNote>12</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>50</id>
        <titre>splom : scatter plot matrices</titre>
        <titre_fr>splom, matrice de nuage de points</titre_fr>
        <comments>&lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/splom.html&quot;&gt;splom&lt;/a&gt; produces Scatter Plot Matrices. The role usually played by &lt;tt&gt;panel&lt;/tt&gt; is taken over by superpanel, which determines how the columns of &lt;tt&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt; are to be arranged for pairwise plots. The only available option currently is &lt;tt&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;

Many of the finer customizations usually done via arguments to high level function like xyplot are instead done by panel.pairs for splom. These include control of axis limits, tick locations and prepanel calcultions. If you are trying to fine-tune your splom plot, definitely look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/panel.pairs.html&quot;&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/a&gt; help page. The scales argument is usually not very useful in splom, and trying to change it may have undesired effects.

</comments>
        <comments_fr>&lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/splom.html&quot;&gt;splom&lt;/a&gt; produit une matrice de nuages de points. Le role habituellement pris par &lt;tt&gt;panel&lt;/tt&gt; est pris ici par &lt;tt&gt;superpanel&lt;/tt&gt; qui détermine comment les colonnes de &lt;tt&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt; doivent être arrangées pour les graphiques bivariées (nuages de points). La seule option disponible pour l'instant est &lt;tt&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;

Les raffinements effectués habituellement via les arguments des fonctions graphiques de haut niveau, comme xyplot sont fait ici par la fonction &lt;tt&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/tt&gt; donnée à splom. On peut par exemple controler les limites des axes et la position des ticks. Avant d'essayer de customiser votre graphique en utilisant splom, regardez la page d'aide de &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/panel.pairs.html&quot;&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/a&gt;. L'argument d'échelle n'est habituellement pas utile pour un graphique splom, essayer de le changer peut avoir des effets indésirables.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>66.4</notemoy>
        <nbNote>5</nbNote>
        <example>splom</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>49</id>
        <titre>splom 2 : scatterplot matrices</titre>
        <titre_fr>matrice de nuages de points (splom)</titre_fr>
        <comments>&lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/splom.html&quot;&gt;splom&lt;/a&gt; produces Scatter Plot Matrices. The role usually played by &lt;tt&gt;panel&lt;/tt&gt; is taken over by superpanel, which determines how the columns of &lt;tt&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt; are to be arranged for pairwise plots. The only available option currently is &lt;tt&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;

Many of the finer customizations usually done via arguments to high level function like xyplot are instead done by panel.pairs for splom. These include control of axis limits, tick locations and prepanel calcultions. If you are trying to fine-tune your splom plot, definitely look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/panel.pairs.html&quot;&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/a&gt; help page. The scales argument is usually not very useful in splom, and trying to change it may have undesired effects.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>&lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/splom.html&quot;&gt;splom&lt;/a&gt; produit une matrice de nuages de points. Le role habituellement pris par &lt;tt&gt;panel&lt;/tt&gt; est pris ici par &lt;tt&gt;superpanel&lt;/tt&gt; qui détermine comment les colonnes de &lt;tt&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt; doivent être arrangées pour les graphiques bivariées (nuages de points). La seule option disponible pour l'instant est &lt;tt&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;

Les raffinements effectués habituellement via les arguments des fonctions graphiques de haut niveau, comme xyplot sont fait ici par la fonction &lt;tt&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/tt&gt; donnée à splom. On peut par exemple controler les limites des axes et la position des ticks. Avant d'essayer de customiser votre graphique en utilisant splom, regardez la page d'aide de &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/lattice/html/panel.pairs.html&quot;&gt;panel.pairs&lt;/a&gt;. L'argument d'échelle n'est habituellement pas utile pour un graphique splom, essayer de le changer peut avoir des effets indésirables.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>64.058823529412</notemoy>
        <nbNote>17</nbNote>
        <example>splom</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>51</id>
        <titre>Times Series : Forecasting</titre>
        <titre_fr>Séries temporelles : prédiction</titre_fr>
        <comments>Here is an example of forecasting an AR(1) process. &lt;tt&gt;arima.sim&lt;/tt&gt; is used to generate a time series from such a process, &lt;tt&gt;arima&lt;/tt&gt; is then used to fit an AR(1) representation given the 200 first observations. Finally &lt;tt&gt;predict&lt;/tt&gt; is used to make the forecast.&lt;br&gt;
See how the confidence band is plotted thanks to &lt;tt&gt;polygon&lt;/tt&gt;</comments>
        <comments_fr>Voici un exemple de prévision d'un processus autorégressif d'ordre 1 : AR(1). La fonction &lt;tt&gt;arima.sim&lt;/tt&gt; est utilisée pour générer une série de 250 observations issue d'un tel processus., &lt;tt&gt;arima&lt;/tt&gt; est ensuite utilisée pour ajuster une représentation AR(1) à partir des 200 premières observations. Finalement, &lt;tt&gt;predict&lt;/tt&gt; est utilisée pour effectuer la prédiction.&lt;br&gt;
Notons comment la bande de confiance est représentée à l'aide de la fonction &lt;tt&gt;polygon&lt;/tt&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>64.59649122807</notemoy>
        <nbNote>114</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>52</id>
        <titre>Lattice : confidence intervals</titre>
        <titre_fr>intervalles de confiance avec lattice</titre_fr>
        <comments>The function plotmeans{gplots} provides an easy option to plot means and confidence intervals for a variable at different levels of a single factor. This code is a workaround to allow plotting of means and confidence intervals of a variable at different levels of multiple factors, using library(lattice) and the xYplot{Hmisc}.&lt;br&gt;

The required confidence intervals can be easily calculated using smean.cl.normal{Hmisc}:
&lt;pre&gt;
tmp &lt;- summarize( x, 
                llist(y,z), 
                smean.cl.normal)
&lt;/pre&gt;
</comments>
        <comments_fr>La fonction &lt;tt&gt;plotmeans&lt;/tt&gt; (gplots) fournit une option pour tracer moyennes et intervalles de confiance d'une variable à différents niveaux d'un facteur. Ce code est issu d'un travail pour dessiner moyenne et intervalle de confiance d'une variable à différents niveaux de &lt;em&gt;plusieurs&lt;/em&gt; facteurs. Ce graphique utilise le package lattice et la fonction xYplot du package Hmisc.&lt;br&gt;
Les intervalles de confiance peuvent être facilement calculés en utilisant la fonction smean.cl.normal du package Hmisc. 

</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>0.33052479537784</notemoy>
        <nbNote>4154</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>53</id>
        <titre>superbarplot</titre>
        <titre_fr>superbarplot</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plot a barplot, with bars nested and ranging from a max to a minimum value. A similar graphic is used on the weather page of the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
A similar graphic on the weather page of the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; shows bars for record highs and lows, normal highs and lows and actual (or predicted) highs or lows for 10 days of weather. This graphic succintly and elegantly displays a wealth of information. Intended as an illustration of the &lt;tt&gt;polygon&lt;/tt&gt; function.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Trace un diagramme en batons, avec des barres alllant de la valeur minimale à la valeur maximale. Un graphique similaire est utilisé pour la page météo u &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Ce graphique présente succintement et élégemment une bonne quantité d'information. Utilise la fonction &lt;tt&gt;polygon&lt;/tt&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>53.089000000001</notemoy>
        <nbNote>20</nbNote>
        <example>superbarplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>54</id>
        <titre>barplot2 : Enhanced Bar Plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>barplot2 : diagramme en batons améliorés</titre_fr>
        <comments>An enhancement of the standard barplot() function. Creates a bar plot with vertical or horizontal bars. Can plot confidence intervals for each bar, a lined grid behind the bars, change plot area color and logarithmic axes may be used.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Une amélioration de la fonction barplot. Cette fonction crée un diagramme en batons vertical ou horizontal. Les intervalles de confiance peuvent être ajoutés pour chaque barre, puis une grille derrière les barres. On peut utiliser des axes logarithmiques et changer les couleurs du graphique.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>67.550561797753</notemoy>
        <nbNote>89</nbNote>
        <example>barplot2</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>55</id>
        <titre>conditionnal histogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>histogramme conditionnel</titre_fr>
        <comments>This is an example of a lattice graph showing histograms of a variable conditionnal to two other variables. See how easy it is with lattice to add a normal density on top of each histogram.&lt;br&gt;
Note also that the background and other parameters can be set using &lt;tt&gt;trellis.par.set&lt;/tt&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphique lattice préente plusieurs histogrammes d'une variable conditionnés par deux autres. Notons comme il est aisé avec lattice d'ajouter une courbe de densité gaussienne à chaque histogramme.&lt;br&gt;
La couleur de fond ainsi que d'autres paramètres sont définis en utilisant la fonction &lt;tt&gt;trellis.par.set&lt;/tt&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>70.911764705881</notemoy>
        <nbNote>34</nbNote>
        <example>histogram</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>56</id>
        <titre>Association Plots</titre>
        <comments>Produce a Cohen-Friendly association plot indicating deviations from independence of rows and columns in a 2-dimensional contingency table. For a two-way contingency table, the signed contribution to Pearson's chi^2 for cell i, j is d_{ij} = (f_{ij} - e_{ij}) / sqrt(e_{ij}), where f_{ij} and e_{ij} are the observed and expected counts corresponding to the cell. In the Cohen-Friendly association plot, each cell is represented by a rectangle that has (signed) height proportional to d_{ij} and width proportional to sqrt(e_{ij}), so that the area of the box is proportional to the difference in observed and expected frequencies. The rectangles in each row are positioned relative to a baseline indicating independence (d_{ij} = 0). If the observed frequency of a cell is greater than the expected one, the box rises above the baseline and is shaded in the color specified by the first element of col, which defaults to black; otherwise, the box falls below the baseline and is shaded in the color specified by the second element of col, which defaults to red.</comments>
        <notemoy>32.5</notemoy>
        <nbNote>2</nbNote>
        <example>assocplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>57</id>
        <titre>bar plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>diagramme en baton</titre_fr>
        <comments>Creates a bar plot with vertical or horizontal bars. Default gray colors are particularly well chosen with the &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=barplot.html&amp;alias=barplot&quot;&gt;barplot&lt;/a&gt; function. The alliance with the &lt;em&gt;dark blue&lt;/em&gt; border is great.&lt;br&gt;
Note that axis annotations are horizontal thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=par.html&amp;alias=par&quot;&gt;par&lt;/a&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Diagramme en batons superposés. Les couleurs par défaut des barres sont du plus bel effet. Elles se marient très bien avec une bordure en &lt;em&gt;dark blue&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Notons également que les annotations sur les axes sont horizontales grace à l'utilisation de la fonction &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=par.html&amp;alias=par&quot;&gt;par&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>1.441823899371</notemoy>
        <nbNote>636</nbNote>
        <example>barplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>58</id>
        <titre>standard bar plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>diagramme en batons</titre_fr>
        <comments>Creates a bar plot with vertical bars. The outputs of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=barplot.html&amp;alias=barplot&quot;&gt;barplot&lt;/a&gt; function is used here to add more information on the graph with the low-level functions &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=mtext.html&amp;alias=mtext&quot;&gt;mtext&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=segments.html&amp;alias=segments&quot;&gt;segments&lt;/a&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Diagramme en batons verticaux. Les sorties de la fonction &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=barplot.html&amp;alias=barplot&quot;&gt;barplot&lt;/a&gt; sont utilisées ici pour ajouter de l'information au graph à l'aide des fonctions de bas niveau &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=mtext.html&amp;alias=mtext&quot;&gt;mtext&lt;/a&gt; et &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=segments.html&amp;alias=segments&quot;&gt;segments&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>64.250000000001</notemoy>
        <nbNote>20</nbNote>
        <example>barplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>59</id>
        <titre>Sun Flower Plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Sun Flower Plot</titre_fr>
        <comments>Multiple points are plotted as “sunflowers” with multiple leaves (“petals”) such that overplotting is visualized instead of accidental and invisible.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les points multiples sont représentés par des &quot;sunflowers&quot; avec plusieurs &quot;pétales&quot;. Ainsi l'affichage de plusieurs points au même endroit est visible et non accidentel et invisible</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>0.1474455720354</notemoy>
        <nbNote>11529</nbNote>
        <example>sunflowerplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>60</id>
        <titre>Balloon plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Balloon plot</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plot a graphical matrix where each cell contains a dot whose size reflects the relative magnitude of the corresponding component.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Représentation d'une matrice de contingence ou chaque cellule contient un point dont l'aire est proportionnelle à la valeur correspondante dans la matrice</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>8.2643171806165</notemoy>
        <nbNote>227</nbNote>
        <example>balloonplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>61</id>
        <titre>Augmented Convex Hull</titre>
        <titre_fr>Enveloppes convexes améliorées</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plots 2D convex hulls or bivariate density contours, one for each group of data. Descriptive statistics are plotted as error bars or confidence ellipses within convex hulls. Marginal distributions as well as a special legend are added by default. </comments>
        <comments_fr>Représentation d'enveloppes convexes 2D ou de lignes de niveaux de densité bivariée, pour chaque groupe. Des statistiques descriptives sont représentées sous forme de barres d'erreur ou d'ellipses de confiance dans les enveloppes convexes. </comments_fr>
        <notemoy>16.135802469136</notemoy>
        <nbNote>81</nbNote>
        <example>chplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>62</id>
        <titre>Curves</titre>
        <titre_fr>Courbes</titre_fr>
        <comments>Draws a curve corresponding to the given function or expression (in x) over the interval [from,to].</comments>
        <comments_fr>Dessine une courbe correspondant à une fonction ou une expression donnée (en x) sur l'intervalle [from,to]</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>24.055555555555</notemoy>
        <nbNote>18</nbNote>
        <example>curve</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>63</id>
        <titre>stars</titre>
        <titre_fr>etoiles</titre_fr>
        <comments>Draw star plots or segment diagrams of a multivariate data set. With one single location, also draws “spider” (or “radar”) plots. &lt;br&gt;Each star plot or segment diagram represents one row of the input &lt;tt&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt;. Variables (columns) start on the right and wind counterclockwise around the circle. The size of the (scaled) column is shown by the distance from the center to the point on the star or the radius of the segment representing the variable.&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=stars.html&amp;alias=stars&quot;&gt;See the help page&lt;/a&gt;

</comments>
        <comments_fr>Dessine des diagrammes en étoiles ou en segments à partir d'un jeu de données multivarié, peut aussi dessiner des diagrammes en &quot;araignée&quot; (ou en &quot;radar&quot;).&lt;br&gt;
Chaque étoile représente une ligne du tableau de données &lt;tt&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt;. Les variables (colonnes) commencent à droite et tournent dans le sens inverse des aiguilles d'une montre autour du cercle. La taille de la colonne (standardisée) est représentée par la distance du centre au point de l'étoile associé à la variable. La page d'aide de la fonction stars peut se trouver  &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=stars.html&amp;alias=stars&quot;&gt;ici&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>67.6875</notemoy>
        <nbNote>16</nbNote>
        <example>stars</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>1</boolForum>
        <urlForum>http://addictedtor.free.fr/phpBB2/viewtopic.php?t=3</urlForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>64</id>
        <titre>ACF and PACF</titre>
        <titre_fr>fonctions d'autocorrélation et d'autocorrélation partielle</titre_fr>
        <comments>The function &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=stats&amp;fun=acf.html&amp;alias=acf&gt;acf&lt;/a&gt; computes (and by default plots) estimates of the autocovariance or autocorrelation function. Function &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=stats&amp;fun=acf.html&amp;alias=pcf&gt;pacf&lt;/a&gt; is the function used for the partial autocorrelations.
The two graph are next to each other thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=par.html&amp;alias=par&quot;&gt;par&lt;/a&gt; function with its &lt;tt&gt;mfrow&lt;/tt&gt; argument. &lt;br/&gt;

</comments>
        <comments_fr>La fonction &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=stats&amp;fun=acf.html&amp;alias=acf&gt;acf&lt;/a&gt; 
calcule (et par défaut trace) une estimation de l'autocovariance ou de la fonction d'autocorrélation. La fonction &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=stats&amp;fun=acf.html&amp;alias=pcf&gt;pacf&lt;/a&gt; est en revanche utilisée pour les autocorrélations partielles.
A l'aide de la fonction &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=par.html&amp;alias=par&quot;&gt;par&lt;/a&gt; et de son argument &lt;tt&gt;mfrow&lt;/tt&gt;, les deux graphs sont juxtaposés.

</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>42.697803030305</notemoy>
        <nbNote>33</nbNote>
        <example>acf</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>65</id>
        <titre>Bollinger Bands</titre>
        <titre_fr>Bollinger Bands</titre_fr>
        <comments>This graph is a particular chart that practioners in Finance 
   like to look at to complement other analyses: &lt;a 
   href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bollinger_bands&quot;&gt;Bollinger 
   Bands&lt;/a&gt; of (typically 2) standard deviation around the current price. 
   The code also colors up-moves and down-moves differently, and shows 
   where day's open and close are relative to the high and low. Relative 
  'dispersion' of the measure and position of price relative to dispersion 
   is shown as well, as are bars for volume. This code is an R translation
   of code by John Bollinger, and updated to pull data directly from
   Yahoo without requiring the functions from the tseries and its packages.
   Running the example require net access to obtain current prices.</comments>
        <notemoy>10.886225416038</notemoy>
        <nbNote>661</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>66</id>
        <titre>heatmap</titre>
        <titre_fr>heatmap</titre_fr>
        <comments>A heat map is a false color image (basically &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=image.html&amp;alias=image&quot;&gt;image&lt;/a&gt;(t(x))) with a dendrogram added to the left side and to the top. Typically, reordering of the rows and columns according to some set of values (row or column means) within the restrictions imposed by the dendrogram is carried out.</comments>
        <notemoy>58.5</notemoy>
        <nbNote>56</nbNote>
        <example>heatmap</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>67</id>
        <titre>cluster plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique de classification</titre_fr>
        <comments>Creates a bivariate plot visualizing a partition (clustering) of the data. All observation are represented by points in the plot, using principal components or multidimensional scaling. Around each cluster an ellipse is drawn.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Representation bivariée d'une partition (classification) des données. Les observations sont représentées par des points sur le graphique (le symbole dépend du groupe de l'individu). Ce graphique utilise l'analyse en composantes principales ou le MDS. Une ellipse est dessinnée autour de chaque groupe.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>0.67660480681473</notemoy>
        <nbNote>3287</nbNote>
        <example>clusplot.default</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>68</id>
        <titre>Geographic cluster analysis</titre>
        <titre_fr>Classification géographique</titre_fr>
        <comments>A simple &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=layout.html&amp;alias=layout&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/a&gt; arrengement. On the left side, usa map with states coloured regarding the result of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=cluster&amp;fun=pam.html&amp;alias=pam&quot;&gt;pam&lt;/a&gt; clustering, colours are chosen thanks to the RColorBrewer package. On the right side, there is a 2d representation of the clusters computed and plotted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=cluster&amp;fun=clusplot.html&amp;alias=clusplot&quot;&gt;clusplot&lt;/a&gt; and also a &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=cluster&amp;fun=silhouette.html&amp;alias=silhouette&quot;&gt;silhouette&lt;/a&gt; plot.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Simple arrangement graphique (&lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=layout.html&amp;alias=layout&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/a&gt;). 
A gauche, la carte des usa coloriée selon les résultats d'une classification &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=cluster&amp;fun=pam.html&amp;alias=pam&quot;&gt;pam&lt;/a&gt;, les couleurs sont choisies à l'aide du package RColorBrewer. A droite, une représentation en 2D des groupes par  &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=cluster&amp;fun=clusplot.html&amp;alias=clusplot&quot;&gt;clusplot&lt;/a&gt;  et aussi la &lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/help/index.html?pack=cluster&amp;fun=silhouette.html&amp;alias=silhouette&quot;&gt;silhouette&lt;/a&gt; de la classification.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>35.111650485438</notemoy>
        <nbNote>103</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>69</id>
        <titre>Linear discriminant analysis</titre>
        <titre_fr>Analyse linéaire discriminante</titre_fr>
        <comments>See the help page for &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=MASS&amp;fun=lda.html&amp;alias=lda&quot;&gt;lda&lt;/a&gt; and its 
&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=MASS&amp;fun=plot.lda.html&amp;alias=lda&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/a&gt; method. </comments>
        <comments_fr>Voir l'aide de &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=MASS&amp;fun=lda.html&amp;alias=lda&quot;&gt;lda&lt;/a&gt; et sa méthode 
&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=MASS&amp;fun=plot.lda.html&amp;alias=lda&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/a&gt;. </comments_fr>
        <notemoy>40.528124999998</notemoy>
        <nbNote>32</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>70</id>
        <titre>2D Histogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Histogramme 2D</titre_fr>
        <comments>The fucntion &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=gplots&amp;fun=hist2d.html&amp;alias=hist2d&quot;&gt;hist2d&lt;/a&gt;
creates a 2-dimensional histogram by cutting the x and y dimensions into &lt;tt&gt;nbins&lt;/tt&gt; sections. A 2-dimensional matrix is then constucted which holds the counts of the number of observed (x,y) pairs that fall into each bin. If show=TRUE, this matrix is then then passed to 
&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=image.html&amp;alias=image&quot;&gt;image&lt;/a&gt; for display.  &lt;br/&gt;
Here a &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=rug.html&amp;alias=rug&quot;&gt;rug&lt;/a&gt; is added to visualize the location of the obervations on both axes.</comments>
        <comments_fr>La fonction &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=gplots&amp;fun=hist2d.html&amp;alias=hist2d&quot;&gt;hist2d&lt;/a&gt;
construit un histogramme en deux dimensions en coupant les variables x et y en &lt;tt&gt;nbins&lt;/tt&gt; intervalles.

Une matrice 2D est alors construite avec les effectifs dans chaque case. La matrice est passée à la fonction 
&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=image.html&amp;alias=image&quot;&gt;image&lt;/a&gt; pour la représentation graphique.  &lt;br/&gt;
Ici, un &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=rug.html&amp;alias=rug&quot;&gt;rug&lt;/a&gt; est ajouté pour visualiser la position des observations sur les deux axes.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>67.648648648647</notemoy>
        <nbNote>37</nbNote>
        <example>hist2d</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>71</id>
        <titre>Diagnostic distribution plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphique de diagnostic de distribution</titre_fr>
        <comments>distplot plots the number of occurrences (counts) against the distribution metameter of the specified distribution. If the distribution fits the data, the plot should show a straight line</comments>
        <notemoy>45.444444444444</notemoy>
        <nbNote>9</nbNote>
        <example>distplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>72</id>
        <titre>(Log) Odds Ratios Plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphique d' Odds Ratios</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plots (log) odds ratios, computed by &lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=vcd&amp;fun=oddsratio.html&amp;alias=oddsratio&quot;&gt;oddsratio&lt;/a&gt; for 2 x 2 x k-tables, along with confidence intervals.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Trace les (log) odds ratios, calculés par la fonction 
&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=vcd&amp;fun=oddsratio.html&amp;alias=oddsratio&quot;&gt;oddsratio&lt;/a&gt;
pour des tables 2 x 2 x k, avec les intervalles de confiance</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>49.666666666667</notemoy>
        <nbNote>12</nbNote>
        <example>plot.oddsratio</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>73</id>
        <titre>Circles Plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Nuages de cercles</titre_fr>
        <comments>A simple pseudo three dimensional scatterplot of circels whose sizes index a thrid variable.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Un simple pseudo nuage de points 3D. Les points sont représentés pae des cercles dont la taille indique une troisième variable.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>38.730769230769</notemoy>
        <nbNote>26</nbNote>
        <example>circlesPlot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>74</id>
        <titre>Gantt Charts</titre>
        <titre_fr>Diagramme de Gantt</titre_fr>
        <comments>Displays a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gantt_chart&quot;&gt;Gantt chart&lt;/a&gt; with priority coloring</comments>
        <comments_fr>Trace un &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gantt_chart&quot;&gt;Diagramme de Gantt&lt;/a&gt; avec 
les priorités sous forme de couleurs</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>19.835937499999</notemoy>
        <nbNote>384</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>75</id>
        <titre>radial.plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Diagramme radial</titre_fr>
        <comments>radial.plot displays a plot of radial lines, polygon(s) or symbols centered at the midpoint of the plot frame, the lengths, vertices or positions corresponding to the numeric magnitudes of the data values. &lt;br/&gt;The radial.plot family of plots is useful for illustrating cyclic data such as wind direction and velocity, activity at different times of the day, and so on. While radial.plot actually does the plotting, another function is usually called for specific types of cyclic data.</comments>
        <notemoy>29.923076923077</notemoy>
        <nbNote>13</nbNote>
        <example>radial.plot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>76</id>
        <titre>Soil Texture Plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Soil Texture Plot</titre_fr>
        <comments>soil.texture displays a triangular plot area on which soil textures defined as proportions of sand, silt and clay can be plotted. Optional grid, vertex labels, soil type divisions and names may also be displayed. If a matrix of soil textures is present, this will be passed to show.soil.texture and the textures will be plotted.</comments>
        <notemoy>70.652173913043</notemoy>
        <nbNote>46</nbNote>
        <example>soil.texture</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>77</id>
        <titre>Box-Percentile plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphique percentile de Box</titre_fr>
        <comments>Box-percentile plots are similiar to boxplots, except box-percentile plots supply more information about the univariate distributions. At any height the width of the irregular &quot;box&quot; is proportional to the percentile of that height, up to the 50th percentile, and above the 50th percentile the width is proportional to 100 minus the percentile. Thus, the width at any given height is proportional to the percent of observations that are more extreme in that direction. As in boxplots, the median, 25th and 75th percentiles are marked with line segments across the box.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Le graphique percentile de Box est similaire aux boxplots, mais plus d'information sur la distribution univariée est représentée. Pour toute hauteur, la largeur  de la &quot;boite&quot; irrégulière est proportionnelle au percentile de cette hauteur, ce jusqu'à la médiane. Ensuite, la largeur est proportionnelle à 100 moins le percentile. Ainsi, la largeur à n'importe quelle hauteur est proportionnelle au pourcentage d'observations qui sont plus extrêmes dans cette direction. Comme pour les boxplots classiques, la mediane, et les quantiles à 25 et 75 % sont représentés par une ligne traversant la boite.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>50.7</notemoy>
        <nbNote>10</nbNote>
        <example>bpplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>78</id>
        <titre>Scatterplot with marginal histograms</titre>
        <titre_fr>Nuages de points avec histogrammes marginaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=layout.html&amp;alias=layout&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/a&gt; allows
you to separate the screen in several parts. The current graphs is a simple scatterplot with marginal histograms.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
That short &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.ucl.ac.be/cgi-bin/getdata?FMPRO?-db=didacomment.fp5&amp;-format=/dida/comment.htm&amp;-Lay=Comment&amp;-SortField=id&amp;-SortOrder=descend&amp;-max=1&amp;id=24&amp;op=eq&amp;-find&quot;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
presents (in french) the steps of creation of that graph.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>&lt;a href=&quot;help/index.html?pack=graphics&amp;fun=layout.html&amp;alias=layout&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/a&gt; permet
de diviser arbitrairement la fenetre graphique en plusieurs parties. Ici, un nuage de points
avec les histogrammes dans les marges.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>78.438596491227</notemoy>
        <nbNote>57</nbNote>
        <example>layout</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>79</id>
        <titre>Colored Dendrogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Dendrogramme en couleurs</titre_fr>
        <comments>This is a colored dendrogram. Each cluster have its color. Plus, the plot displays a 
factor below in order to compare it with the clusters resulting of the tree cut. On the left is shown the evolution of the hubertgamma criterion.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Un dendrogramme en couleurs. Chaque groupe a sa couleur. Le graphique présente 
une variable qualitative supplémentaire de façon à la comparer avec les groupes 
résultant de la coupe de l'arbre. A gauche est montrée l'évolution du critère hubertgamma.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>17.309941520472</notemoy>
        <nbNote>513</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>80</id>
        <titre>Matlab quiver function</titre>
        <titre_fr>equivalent de la fonction quiver de Matlab</titre_fr>
        <comments>a simple version of matlab's quiver function. 
A vector, tensor, field, 2d arrow plot.
More comprehensive information is available in the :
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tolstoy.newcastle.edu.au/R/help/01c/2711.html&quot;&gt;R-help thread &lt;/a&gt;. That graph is also available in one &lt;a href=&quot;http://fawn.unibw-hamburg.de/cgi-bin/Rwiki.pl?QuiverPlot&quot;&gt;R Wiki Page&lt;/a&gt;</comments>
        <comments_fr>Une simple version de la fonction quiver de Matlab. Un graphique de vecteur, tenseur, champ, fleches en 2d.
Pour plus d'information, voir la &lt;a href=&quot;http://tolstoy.newcastle.edu.au/R/help/01c/2711.html&quot;&gt;discussion R-help&lt;/a&gt;.
Ce graphique est également disponible sur une page de la &lt;a href=&quot;http://fawn.unibw-hamburg.de/cgi-bin/Rwiki.pl?QuiverPlot&quot;&gt;Wiki de R&lt;/a&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>44.066666666666</notemoy>
        <nbNote>15</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>81</id>
        <titre>Scatterplot with Tufte axes</titre>
        <titre_fr>Nuages de points avec axes à la Tufte</titre_fr>
        <comments>&lt;b&gt;fancyaxis()&lt;/b&gt;
draws an axis showing information about the marginal distribution of a variable as suggested in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edwardtufte.com/tufte/books_vdqi&quot;&gt;The Visual Display of Quantitative Information&lt;/a&gt; by Edward Tufte.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;axisstripchart()&lt;/b&gt; draws a bar plot on an axis, showing the marginal distribution of the respective variable.
&lt;br&gt;
This graph shows the how the fancyaxis() and axisstripchart() functions can be used. In addition, the points have been coloured to increase the dimensionality of the graph. Red indicates that the previous eruption was longer than 180 seconds, blue indicates that it was shorter than 180 seconds.
&lt;br&gt;
It appears that when one eruption is of the short type (shorter than 180 seconds), the next one will probably be of the long type (longer than 180 seconds). This is apparent from the graph, and is backed up by the numbers. 36% of eruptions are short. Where the previous eruption is short, only 6% of eruptions are short, but where the previous eruption is long, 52% of eruptions are short.</comments>
        <comments_fr>&lt;b&gt;fancyaxis()&lt;/b&gt;
dessine un axe contenant de l'information sur la distribution marginale d'une variable
comme il est suggéré dans  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edwardtufte.com/tufte/books_vdqi&quot;&gt;The Visual Display of Quantitative Information&lt;/a&gt; de Edward Tufte.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;axisstripchart()&lt;/b&gt; 
dessine un diagramme en baton sur un axe permettant d'afficher la distribution
marginale de la variable considérée
&lt;br&gt;
Ce graph montre comment utiliser les fonctions ancyaxis() et axisstripchart(). De plus,
les points sont colorés pour ajouter une dimension de plus au graphique. Le rouge
indique que la précédente eruption était plus longue que 180 secondes, Le bleu indique qu'elle était plus courte que 180 secondes.
&lt;br&gt;
Il apparait que quand une eruption est courte (inferieure a 180 secondes), la prochaine
sera probablement longue. Cela se lit sur le graph, et est confirmé par les chiffres,
36% des eruptions sont courtes. Quand une eruption est courte, seulement 6% des eruptions qui suivent sont courtes, mais si la précédente est longue, 52% des eruptions qui suivent sont courtes.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>74.954545454547</notemoy>
        <nbNote>88</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>82</id>
        <titre>Multiple histogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Histogramme multiple</titre_fr>
        <comments>Given a list, plots a side-by-side barplot containing the histograms of the elements</comments>
        <comments_fr>Dispose sous forme de diagrammes en batons, les histogrammes de chaque élément d'une liste</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>71.805309734513</notemoy>
        <nbNote>113</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>83</id>
        <titre>barplot filled with symbols</titre>
        <titre_fr>Diagramme en batons rempli de symboles</titre_fr>
        <comments>Produces a barplot where each piece of the barplot is filled with the number of symbols equal to the size of the bar</comments>
        <comments_fr>Produit un diagramme en baton (barplot) ou chaque baton est rempli d'un nombre de symboles égal à la taille du baton</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>20.342105263158</notemoy>
        <nbNote>19</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>84</id>
        <titre>Conditional (Regression) Tree</titre>
        <titre_fr>Arbre de regression conditionnel</titre_fr>
        <comments>Conditional trees estimate a regression relationship by binary recursive partitioning in a conditional inference framework. Roughly, the algorithm works as follows: 
&lt;br/&gt;1) Test the global null hypothesis of independence between any of the input variables and the response (which may be multivariate as well). Stop if this hypothesis cannot be rejected. Otherwise select the input variable with strongest association to the resonse. This association is measured by a p-value corresponding to a test for the partial null hypothesis of a single input variable and the response. 
&lt;br/&gt;2) Implement a binary split in the selected input variable. 
&lt;br/&gt;3) Recursively repeate steps 1) and 2).

&lt;br/&gt;
This one is a &lt;b&gt;regression&lt;/b&gt; tree, so the distribution in each terminal node is shown as a boxplot.</comments>
        <notemoy>68.049999999999</notemoy>
        <nbNote>40</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>85</id>
        <titre>Conditional (Classification) Tree</titre>
        <titre_fr>Arbre de classification conditionnel</titre_fr>
        <comments>Conditional trees estimate a regression relationship by binary recursive partitioning in a conditional inference framework. Roughly, the algorithm works as follows: 
&lt;br/&gt;1) Test the global null hypothesis of independence between any of the input variables and the response (which may be multivariate as well). Stop if this hypothesis cannot be rejected. Otherwise select the input variable with strongest association to the resonse. This association is measured by a p-value corresponding to a test for the partial null hypothesis of a single input variable and the response. 
&lt;br/&gt;2) Implement a binary split in the selected input variable. 
&lt;br/&gt;3) Recursively repeate steps 1) and 2).
&lt;br/&gt; This one is a &lt;b&gt;classification&lt;/b&gt; tree. Repartition is shown as barplots in the terminal nodes</comments>
        <notemoy>54.862068965517</notemoy>
        <nbNote>29</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>86</id>
        <titre>Conditional (Survival analysis) Tree</titre>
        <titre_fr>Arbre de survie conditionnel</titre_fr>
        <comments>Conditional trees estimate a regression relationship by binary recursive partitioning in a conditional inference framework. Roughly, the algorithm works as follows: 
&lt;br/&gt;1) Test the global null hypothesis of independence between any of the input variables and the response (which may be multivariate as well). Stop if this hypothesis cannot be rejected. Otherwise select the input variable with strongest association to the resonse. This association is measured by a p-value corresponding to a test for the partial null hypothesis of a single input variable and the response. 
&lt;br/&gt;2) Implement a binary split in the selected input variable. 
&lt;br/&gt;3) Recursively repeate steps 1) and 2).
&lt;br/&gt; This is a survival analysis tree. Conditionnal survival is produced in each terminal node of the tree</comments>
        <notemoy>48.021951219513</notemoy>
        <nbNote>41</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>87</id>
        <titre>Chernoff faces</titre>
        <titre_fr>les visages de Chernoff</titre_fr>
        <comments>representation of the rows of a data matrix by faces.
The features paramters of this implementation are: 
&lt;br/&gt;1-height of face
&lt;br/&gt;2-width of face
&lt;br/&gt;3-shape of face
&lt;br/&gt;4-height of mouth
&lt;br/&gt;5-width of mouth
&lt;br/&gt;6-curve of smile
&lt;br/&gt;7-height of eyes
&lt;br/&gt;8-width of eyes
&lt;br/&gt;9-height of hair
&lt;br/&gt;10-width of hair
&lt;br/&gt;11-styling of hair
&lt;br/&gt;12-height of nose
&lt;br/&gt;13-width of nose
&lt;br/&gt;14-width of ears
&lt;br/&gt;15-height of ears.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Représente les linidvidus d'une matrice par des visages.
Cette implémentation est ainsi paramétrée :
&lt;br/&gt;1-hauteur du visage
&lt;br/&gt;2-largeur du visage
&lt;br/&gt;3-forme du visage
&lt;br/&gt;4-hauteur de la bouche
&lt;br/&gt;5-largeur de la bouche
&lt;br/&gt;6-sourire
&lt;br/&gt;7-hauteur des yeux
&lt;br/&gt;8-largeur des yeux
&lt;br/&gt;9-hauteur des cheveux
&lt;br/&gt;10-largeur des cheveux
&lt;br/&gt;11-style de coiffure
&lt;br/&gt;12-hauteur du nez
&lt;br/&gt;13-largeur du nez
&lt;br/&gt;14-largeur des oreilles
&lt;br/&gt;15-hauteur des oreilles</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>49.876623376626</notemoy>
        <nbNote>154</nbNote>
        <example>faces</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>88</id>
        <titre>Tests and Mathematical annotations</titre>
        <titre_fr>Théorie des test et annotations mathématiques</titre_fr>
        <comments>This code illustrate how to add Mathematical annotations in a plot, how to play around with polygons and curves.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce code montre comment ajouter des formules mathématiques à un graphique, comment jouer avec les polygones et les courbes.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>71.250000000001</notemoy>
        <nbNote>40</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>89</id>
        <titre>Histogram with equal counts</titre>
        <titre_fr>Histogramme avec effectifs égaux</titre_fr>
        <comments>Histogram with equal counts. The breaks are computed by the quantiles. This example also shows how one can specify colors the rgb way, how to add a curve with lines, and how to control the type of line with lty.


&lt;br/&gt;Based on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/Rhelp02a/archive/29972.html&quot;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt;
 of Hamish Macintyre on R-help.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Histogramme avec effectif égaux. Les intervalles sont calculés à l'aide des quantiles.
Cet exemple montre aussi comment spécifier les couleurs à la RGB, comment ajouter une courbe avec lines, et comment controler le type de ligne avec lty.

&lt;br/&gt;Basé sur une &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/Rhelp02a/archive/29972.html&quot;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt;
 deHamish Macintyre sur R-help.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>39.021739130437</notemoy>
        <nbNote>46</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>90</id>
        <titre>4D contour plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>lignes de niveaux 4D</titre_fr>
        <comments>&lt;p&gt;This plot visualizes four-dimensional data -- i.e., a data set in which

two control variables jointly affect two response variables. The control

variables are shown along x- and y-axes. The first response is shown by

filled contours (colored areas); the second response, by heavy unfilled

contours.


&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleague Phil Goodyear developed this type of graph years ago, and I

recently implemented it in R. (Goodyear, C. P. 1993. Spawning stock biomass

per recruit in fisheries management: foundation and current use. Canadian

Special Publication of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences 120: 67-81.)
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The example, a simplified analysis of black sea bass, shows yield and

spawning potential from different fishing regimes. The data were generated

assuming that fishing follows an S-shaped (logistic) relationship with age.

On the x-axis is the rate of fishing mortality applied to the oldest fish

(control variable #1); on the y-axis is the age at which fish are subject

to 50% of that rate (control variable #2). The two response variables

are values of yield per recruit (YPR) and spawning potential ratio (SPR)

expected. Yield per recruit is the weight landed per fish entering the

population; SPR is the amount of spawning per fish relative to an unfished

population.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The trade-off between yield and spawning is illustrated in this example.

For example, SPR &gt; 0.8 is achieved only at very low values of F, where the

heavy contours show YPR of less than 40 g. The plot also shows (e.g.)

that to simultaneously obtain YPR &gt; 90 and SPR &gt; 0.4, one must set F above

about 1.2 and simultaneously set the age at 50% selection at about 5.5 yrs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
This is a revised version of the graph. The original one is still available 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/sources/old/source_90_version1.R&quot;&gt;here for the source&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://addictedtor.free.fr/graphiques/graphiques/old/graph_90_version1.png&quot;&gt;here for the png file&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</comments>
        <notemoy>63.584905660378</notemoy>
        <nbNote>53</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <urlForum></urlForum>
        <px_w>548</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>91</id>
        <titre>Bangdiwala's Observer Agreement Chart</titre>
        <comments>Representation of a k by k confusion matrix, where the observed and expected diagonal elements are represented by superposed black and white rectangles, respectively. The function also computes a statistic measuring the strength of agreement (relation of respective area sums). &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
graph &lt;a href=&quot;RGraphGallery.php?graph=33&quot;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt; also uses agreementplot.</comments>
        <notemoy>40.888888888889</notemoy>
        <nbNote>9</nbNote>
        <example>agreementplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>92</id>
        <titre>Coplot for Contingency Tables</titre>
        <titre_fr>Coplot pour tables de contingence</titre_fr>
        <comments>cotabplot is a generic function for creating trellis-like coplots (conditional plots) for contingency tables. cotabplot takes on computing the conditioning information and setting up the trellis display, and then relies on a panel function to create plots from the full table and the conditioning information.</comments>
        <notemoy>2.8226600985221</notemoy>
        <nbNote>203</nbNote>
        <example>cotabplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>576</px_w>
        <px_h>415</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>93</id>
        <titre>Double decker plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Double decker plot</titre_fr>
        <comments>

Doubledecker plots visualize the dependence of one categorical (typically binary) variable on further categorical variables. Formally, they are mosaic plots with vertical splits for all dimensions (antecedents) except the last one, which represents the dependent variable (consequent). The last variable is visualized by horizontal splits, no space between the tiles, and separate colors for the levels.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les &quot;doubledecker plot&quot;  permettent de visualiser la dépendance d'une variable catégorielle (typiquement binaire) sur d'autres variables catégorielles. Il s'agit de mosaiques avec des coupures verticales pour toutes les dimensions (causes) sauf la dernière qui représente la variable dépendante (conséquence). La dernière variable est visualisée par des coupures horizontales, sans espace de séparation et avec une couleur par modalité.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>55</notemoy>
        <nbNote>6</nbNote>
        <example>doubledecker</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>627</px_w>
        <px_h>408</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>94</id>
        <titre>Extended mosaic plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Mosaiques améliorées</titre_fr>
        <comments>Mosaic displays have been suggested in the statistical literature by Hartigan and Kleiner (1984) and have been extended by Friendly (1994). mosaicplot is a base graphics implementation and mosaic is a much more flexible and extensible grid implementation.
&lt;br/&gt;

A mosaic plot is an area proportional visualization of a (possibly higher-dimensional) table of expected frequencies. It is composed of tiles (corresponding to the cells) created by recursive vertical and horizontal splits of a square. The area of each tile is proportional to the corresponding cell entry, given the dimensions of previous splits.
&lt;br/&gt;

An extended mosaic plot, in addition, visualizes the fit of a particular log-linear model. Typically, this is done by residual-based shadings where color and/or outline of the tiles visualize sign, size and possibly significance of the corresponding residual.
&lt;br/&gt;

In contrast to the mosaicplot function in graphics, the splits start with the horizontal direction by default to match the printed output of structable. </comments>
        <comments_fr>Les mosaiques ont été suggérées par Hartigan et Kleiner (1984) et ont été améliorées par Friendly (1994). mosaicplot est une implémentation standard alors que mosaic est une implémentation beaucoup plus flexible et étendable basée sur le système grid.&lt;br/&gt;

Une mosaique est une surface de visualisation proportionnelle d'une table (qui peut être de grande dimension) de fréquences attendues. Elle est composée de &quot;tiles&quot; (correspondant aux cellules de la table créés par coupures récursives horizontales et verticales d'un carré. L'aire de chaque &quot;tile&quot; est proportionnelle à l'effectif de la cellule correspondante, sachant les dimensions des précédentes coupures.&lt;br/&gt;

Une mosaique étendue, visualise en plus, l'ajustement d'un modèle log-linéaire particulier. Typiquement, ceci est effectué en jouant avec les couleurs. 
&lt;br/&gt;

Contrairement à la fonction mosaicplot du package graphics, les coupes sont effectuées de façon horizontale par défaut de façon à correspondre au résultat imprimé par la fonction structable  </comments_fr>
        <notemoy>58.173913043479</notemoy>
        <nbNote>23</nbNote>
        <example>mosaic</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>95</id>
        <titre>Extended Association Plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphiques d'association étendus</titre_fr>
        <comments>Association plots have been suggested by Cohen (1980) and extended by Friendly (1992) and provide a means for visualizing the residuals of an independence model for a contingency table.&lt;br/&gt;

assoc is a generic function and currently has a default method and a formula interface. Both are high-level interfaces to the strucplot function, and produce (extended) association plots. Most of the functionality is described there, such as specification of the independence model, labeling, legend, spacing, shading, and other graphical parameters.&lt;br/&gt;

For a contingency table, the signed contribution to Pearson's chi^2 for cell {ij... k} is

&lt;pre&gt;
d_{ij...k} = (f_{ij...k} - e_{ij...k}) / 
                sqrt(e_{ij...k})
&lt;/pre&gt;

where f_{ij...k} and e_{ij...k} are the observed and expected counts corresponding to the cell. In the association plot, each cell is represented by a rectangle that has (signed) height proportional to d_{ij...k} and width proportional to sqrt(e_{ij...k}), so that the area of the box is proportional to the difference in observed and expected frequencies. The rectangles in each row are positioned relative to a baseline indicating independence (d_{ij...k} = 0). If the observed frequency of a cell is greater than the expected one, the box rises above the baseline, and falls below otherwise.
&lt;br/&gt;

Additionally, the residuals can be colored depending on a specified shading scheme (see Meyer et al., 2003). Package vcd offers a range of residual-based shadings (see the shadings help page). Some of them allow, e.g., the visualization of test statistics. </comments>
        <notemoy>63.666666666667</notemoy>
        <nbNote>3</nbNote>
        <example>assoc</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>96</id>
        <titre>Ternary Diagram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Diagramme ternaire</titre_fr>
        <comments>Visualizes compositional, 3-dimensional data in an equilateral triangle.&lt;br/&gt;

A points' coordinates are found by computing the gravity center of mass points using the data entries as weights. Thus, the coordinates of a point 
&lt;pre&gt;P(a,b,c), a + b + c = 1&lt;/pre&gt;, are: 
&lt;pre&gt;P(b + c/2, c * sqrt(3)/2)&lt;/pre&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Visaulise dans un jeu de données à 3 dimensions dans un triangle equilatéral.&lt;br/&gt;

Les coordonnées se trouvent en calculant les barycentres des points de masses (sommets du triangle) en utilisant les données comme poids. Donc, les coordonnés d'un point 
&lt;pre&gt;
P(a,b,c)  ; a + b + c = 1
&lt;/pre&gt;
sont : 
&lt;pre&gt;
x = b + c/2,
y = c * sqrt(3) / 2
&lt;/pre&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>68.387755102041</notemoy>
        <nbNote>49</nbNote>
        <example>ternaryplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>97</id>
        <titre>Rose diagram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Rose diagram</titre_fr>
        <comments>Creates a rose diagram of a circular data set.&lt;br/&gt;
The circumference of the circle is split into groups, the number of groups specified by bins. For each group, a sector is drawn. The radii of the sectors are by default equal to the square root of the relative frequencies of observations in each group. This ensures that the area of the sector is proportional to the group frequency. The length of the radii can be controlled by varying the parameter prop.</comments>
        <notemoy>54.037914691948</notemoy>
        <nbNote>211</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>98</id>
        <titre>Restart-from-10-clusters colored dendrogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Dendrogramme en couleurs à partir de groupes</titre_fr>
        <comments>Hierarchical clustering may start from clusters created by an other method. That plot shows the dendrogram so created. The triangles have base length proportionnal to the num ber of observations in each starting cluster, and so allows to view that number.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Une classification hiérarchique peut partir de groupes créés par une autre méthode. Ce graphique montre le dendrogramme ainsi que le nombre d'individus dans les groupes de départ, par l'intermédiaire de la largeur de la base du triangle.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>67</notemoy>
        <nbNote>11</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>99</id>
        <titre>ROC curve</titre>
        <titre_fr>courbe ROC</titre_fr>
        <comments>ROC curve</comments>
        <comments_fr>courbe ROC</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>41.500000000001</notemoy>
        <nbNote>34</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>100</id>
        <titre>ROC curve with cross validation</titre>
        <titre_fr>courbe ROC avec validation croisée</titre_fr>
        <comments>ROC curve with cross validation</comments>
        <comments_fr>courbe ROC avec validation croisée</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>59.088235294116</notemoy>
        <nbNote>51</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>101</id>
        <titre>Frequency polygon</titre>
        <titre_fr>Polygones des fréquences</titre_fr>
        <comments>The frequency polygon is a density etsimator based on the histogram. It just consists of linking the mid points of the histogram bars, which is quite easy to do with R. The frequency  polygon is continuous and then smoother than the histogram. However, it is not derivable in all points. &lt;br/&gt;
This code is based on an &lt;a href=&quot;http://comments.gmane.org/gmane.comp.lang.r.general/47165&quot;&gt;R-help question by Roger Lundqvist&lt;/a&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Le polygone des fréquences est un estimateur de la densité basé su l'histogramme. En effet, il consiste simplement à lier les milieux des barres de l'histogramme, ce qui se révèle être assez facile à faire avec R. Le polygone des fréquences est continu et donc plus lisse que l'histogramme, cependant il n'est pas dérivable partout.&lt;br/&gt;
Ce code est basé sur une &lt;a href=&quot;http://comments.gmane.org/gmane.comp.lang.r.general/47165&quot;&gt;
question R-help de Roger Lundqvist&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>1.5489977728285</notemoy>
        <nbNote>1796</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>102</id>
        <titre>The boxplot friends</titre>
        <titre_fr>Les amis du boxplot</titre_fr>
        <comments>Some boxplot-like methods. The fisrt figure show the underlying density of the random generated data: a normal mixture of two components.
Then, from left to right are plotted variations around the idea of a boxplot.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The boxplot itself, which concentrates on the central bulk of the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The HDR boxplot, which looks at the zone of highest density &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Violin plot, that uses kernel estimator of the density&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Box-Percentile plot, same as boxplot, but showing more information about the density&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Only the violin plot and the HDR boxplot capture the bimodality in that dataset. Given that the dataset is truly bimodal, they are, in that case, better than the standard boxplot and the Box percentile plot.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Quelques amis du boxplot. La première figure montre la densité sous-jacente du jeu de données généré aléatoirement selon un mélange de deux composantes gaussiennes. Ensuite, de gauche à droite sont représentés quelques variations autour de l'idée de boxplot :
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Le boxplot se concentre sur la masse centrale des données&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Le HDR boxplot, qui regarde les zones de forte densité&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Le violin plot, qui utilise une estimation à noyaux de la densité&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Le Box percentile plot, équivalent du boxplot, mais affichant plus d'information sur la densité&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Sur cet exemple, seuls les violin plot et HDR boxplot captent la bimodalité. Ils surpassent donc boxplots et Box percentiles plot, sachant que le jeu de données est réellement bimodal.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>66.068965517242</notemoy>
        <nbNote>58</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>300</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>103</id>
        <titre>Highest density regions</titre>
        <titre_fr>Zones de grandes densités</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plot of the density (as it is estimated by the kernel method) and the highest density regions.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
Hyndman, R.J. (1996) Computing and graphing highest density regions
&lt;EM&gt;American Statistician&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;50&lt;/B&gt;, 120-126.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Graphique de la densité (estimée par les noyaux) et des zones de grandes densités&lt;br/&gt;
Voir :
Hyndman, R.J. (1996) Computing and graphing highest density regions
&lt;EM&gt;American Statistician&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;50&lt;/B&gt;, 120-126.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>69.187499999999</notemoy>
        <nbNote>16</nbNote>
        <example>hdr</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>104</id>
        <titre>Bivariate Highest density regions</titre>
        <titre_fr>Zones de grandes densités en 2d</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plot of the density in 2d space (as it is estimated by the kernel method) and the highest density regions. The (estimated) mode is located by a circle inside one of the zone of high density. The outliers are highlighted with a dot.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
Hyndman, R.J. (1996) Computing and graphing highest density regions
&lt;EM&gt;American Statistician&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;50&lt;/B&gt;, 120-126.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Graphique de la densité en 2d (estimée par les noyaux) et des zones de grandes densités. Le mode (estimé) est localisé par un cercle à l'intérieur d'une des zones de haute densité. Les points aberrants sont mis en valeur avec des points.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Voir :&lt;br/&gt;
Hyndman, R.J. (1996) Computing and graphing highest density regions
&lt;EM&gt;American Statistician&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;50&lt;/B&gt;, 120-126.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>60.157894736842</notemoy>
        <nbNote>19</nbNote>
        <example>hdr.boxplot.2d</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>105</id>
        <titre>Conditionned Highest density regions</titre>
        <titre_fr>Zones de grandes densité conditionnées</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plot of highest density regions for a conditional density estimate. 
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Reference : &lt;br/&gt;
Hyndman, R.J., Bashtannyk, D.M. and Grunwald, G.K. (1996)
&quot;Estimating and visualizing conditional densities&quot;. &lt;EM&gt;Journal of
Computational and Graphical Statistics&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;5&lt;/B&gt;, 315-336.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Tracé des zones de grandes densités pour une estimation conditionnée de la densité. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Voir : &lt;br/&gt;
Hyndman, R.J., Bashtannyk, D.M. and Grunwald, G.K. (1996)
&quot;Estimating and visualizing conditional densities&quot;. &lt;EM&gt;Journal of
Computational and Graphical Statistics&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;5&lt;/B&gt;, 315-336.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>0.34565119423171</notemoy>
        <nbNote>2219</nbNote>
        <example>hdr.cde</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>106</id>
        <titre>Spie chart</titre>
        <titre_fr>spie chart (camembert)</titre_fr>
        <comments>Spie charts are useful to compare two partitions, the first one sets the angles of the slices and the second one sets the radii.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
D. G. Feitelson (2003), &quot;Comparing Partitions with Spie Charts&quot;. School of Computer Science and Engineering, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~feit/papers/Spie03TR.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~feit/papers/Spie03TR.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Michael Friendly (2000), Gallery of Data Vizualisation : The Best and Worst of Statistical Graphics. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.yorku.ca/SCS/Gallery/&quot;&gt;http://www.math.yorku.ca/SCS/Gallery/&lt;/a&gt;</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les spie charts sont utiles pour comparer deux partitions.  La première spécifie les angles des tranches tandis que la seconde règle les rayons.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
D. G. Feitelson (2003), &quot;Comparing Partitions with Spie Charts&quot;. School of Computer Science and Engineering, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~feit/papers/Spie03TR.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~feit/papers/Spie03TR.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Michael Friendly (2000), Gallery of Data Vizualisation : The Best and Worst of Statistical Graphics. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.yorku.ca/SCS/Gallery/&quot;&gt;http://www.math.yorku.ca/SCS/Gallery/&lt;/a&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>10.360465116278</notemoy>
        <nbNote>86</nbNote>
        <example>plot.spie</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>107</id>
        <titre>R Colors in the RGB space</titre>
        <titre_fr>Les couleurs de R dans l'espace RVB</titre_fr>
        <comments>That graph displays in the 3D rgb space the named colors of R.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphique montre dans l'espace RVB en 3d les couleurs nommées de R.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>29.847457627119</notemoy>
        <nbNote>59</nbNote>
        <example>scatterplot3d</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>108</id>
        <titre>rainbow in the RGB space</titre>
        <titre_fr>arc en ciel dans l'espace RVB</titre_fr>
        <comments>A rainbow of 201 colors is displayed in the 3d RGB space.</comments>
        <comments_fr>un arc en ciel de 201 couleurs est disposé dans l'espace 3d RVB.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>64.876249999999</notemoy>
        <nbNote>80</nbNote>
        <example>scatterplot3d</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>109</id>
        <titre>Quantile regression</titre>
        <titre_fr>Régression quantiles</titre_fr>
        <comments>A graph for presenting individual growth with time in a population with:
&lt;br/&gt; - Histograms of size distribution with time,
&lt;br/&gt; - Quantile regressions for the median and 5% / 95% percentiles,
&lt;br/&gt; - A graph quantile residuals using boxplots around the median model.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
This graph is Fig. 2 of the paper: &lt;br/&gt;
Grosjean, PH, Ch. Spirlet &amp; M. Jangoux,
 2003. A functional growth model with intraspecific competition applied to a
 sea urchin, Paracentrotus lividus. Can. J. Fish. Aquat. Sci., 60:237-246.
</comments>
        <comments_fr>Un graph pour présenter la croissance individuelle avec le temps dans une population avec :
&lt;br/&gt; - Histogramme de la distribution de la taille en fonction du temps,
&lt;br/&gt; - Régression quantiles pour la médiane et les quantiles à 5% et 95%,
&lt;br/&gt; - Un graph quantiles/résidus utilisant les boxplots autour de la médiane.
&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
Ce graph est la figure 2 du papier :&lt;br/&gt;
Grosjean, PH, Ch. Spirlet &amp; M. Jangoux,
 2003. A functional growth model with intraspecific competition applied to a
 sea urchin, Paracentrotus lividus. Can. J. Fish. Aquat. Sci., 60:237-246.
</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>82.293493333339</notemoy>
        <nbNote>375</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>110</id>
        <titre>hexbin 2d generalization of boxplot</titre>
        <titre_fr>generalisation 2d du boxplot avec des grilles hexagonales</titre_fr>
        <comments>This is a 2D generalization of boxplot. Data is split in hexagonal bins. </comments>
        <comments_fr>Une généralisation en 2D du boxplot. Les données sont divisées en hexagones</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>27.75</notemoy>
        <nbNote>16</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>111</id>
        <titre>hexbins</titre>
        <titre_fr>hexbins</titre_fr>
        <comments>Density estimation by hexagonal bins.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Estimation de densité par hexagones</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>51.173913043477</notemoy>
        <nbNote>23</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>112</id>
        <titre>The Bagplot : 2D boxplot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Le bagplot : un boxplot en 2D</titre_fr>
        <comments>The bagplot is a 2D generalization of the boxplot. 
The red asterisk is the bivariate median. The dark blue region is the bag, which contains 50% of the observations with greatest bivariate depth. The other blue region is called the loop, it contains observations that are in the fence (the bag expanded 3 times). 
Observations outside the fence are outliers regarding the concept of depth, they are too far away from the data's central bulk.
&lt;br/&gt;
Source code is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wiwi.uni-bielefeld.de/~wolf/software/R-wtools/bagplot/bagplot.R&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
Michael Friendly (2000), &lt;a href=http://www.math.yorku.ca/SCS/Gallery/&quot;&gt;Gallery of Data Vizualisation&lt;/a&gt; : The Best and Worst of Statistical Graphics. 
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
P. J. Rousseeuw, I. Ruts, and J. W. Tukey (1999). &lt;a href=&quot;ftp://ftp.win.ua.ac.be/pub/preprints/99/Bagbiv99.pdf&quot;&gt;The bagplot: A bivariate boxplot&lt;/a&gt;. The American Statistician, 53:382-387.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
H.P. Wolf (2005). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wiwi.uni-bielefeld.de/~wolf/software/R-wtools/bagplot/bagplot.pdf&quot;&gt;A rough R Impementation of the Bagplot&lt;/a&gt;



</comments>
        <comments_fr>Le bagplot est une généralisation 2D du boxplot.

&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
Michael Friendly (2000), &lt;a href=http://www.math.yorku.ca/SCS/Gallery/&quot;&gt;Gallery of Data Vizualisation&lt;/a&gt; : The Best and Worst of Statistical Graphics. 
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
P. J. Rousseeuw, I. Ruts, and J. W. Tukey (1999). &lt;a href=&quot;ftp://ftp.win.ua.ac.be/pub/preprints/99/Bagbiv99.pdf&quot;&gt;The bagplot: A bivariate boxplot&lt;/a&gt;. The American Statistician, 53:382-387.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
H.P. Wolf (2005). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wiwi.uni-bielefeld.de/~wolf/software/R-wtools/bagplot/bagplot.pdf&quot;&gt;A rough R Impementation of the Bagplot&lt;/a&gt;


</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>77.210317460316</notemoy>
        <nbNote>126</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>113</id>
        <titre>US 2004 elections map</titre>
        <titre_fr>carte des élections américaines 2004</titre_fr>
        <comments>This plot is based on a plot that appeared in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/packages/khtml/2004/11/03/politics/20041103_px_ELECT_GRAPHIC.html&quot;&gt;New York Times flash-based editoral&lt;/a&gt;. Note that there are some differences in the maps shown here and the NYT maps, most notably with respect to some missing data in some New England states, some mismatches in county names, and the representation of NYC.
&lt;br/&gt;
Source code and data to generate the graphic (and other in pdf) is available in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ai.rug.nl/~hedderik/R/US2004/&quot;&gt; author's webpage&lt;/a&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphique est basé sur une animation flash du &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/packages/khtml/2004/11/03/politics/20041103_px_ELECT_GRAPHIC.html&quot;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;. Notons qu'il y a quelques différences entre la carte présentée ici et la carte du NYT, en particulier due à des valeurs manquantes dans certains états de New England, quelques confusions dans le nom des contés, et la représentation de New York City.&lt;br/&gt;
Le code source et les données nécessaire à la production de ce graphique sont disponibles sur la &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ai.rug.nl/~hedderik/R/US2004/&quot;&gt;page web de l'auteur&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>9.2824675324672</notemoy>
        <nbNote>770</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>1</boolForum>
        <urlForum>http://addictedtor.free.fr/phpBB2/viewtopic.php?t=4</urlForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>350</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>114</id>
        <titre>Meta analysis plot (forest plot)</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique de meta analyse</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plot confidence intervals with boxes indicating the sample size/precision and a diamond indicating a summary confidence interval. </comments>
        <comments_fr>Trace des intervalles de confiance avec des boites indiquant le nombre d'individus ou la précision et un diamand indiquant un intervalle de confiance résumé. </comments_fr>
        <notemoy>38.061643835615</notemoy>
        <nbNote>73</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>115</id>
        <titre>Funnel plot for publication bias</titre>
        <comments>Plots the treatment difference for trials against the size of the trial (or other specified variable). Asymmetry in the plot often indicates publication bias.</comments>
        <notemoy>35.25</notemoy>
        <nbNote>12</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>116</id>
        <titre>3D barplot</titre>
        <titre_fr>diagramme en batons 3D</titre_fr>
        <comments>Playing with scatterplot3d, it is possible to draw a 3D barplot. The trick is to use type=&quot;h&quot; and lwd=5 for a solid line looking like a bar.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
References :
&lt;br/&gt;Ligges, U., and Maechler, M. (2003): Scatterplot3d - an R Package for Visualizing Multivariate Data. Journal of Statistical Software 8(11), 1-20. http://www.jstatsoft.org/
</comments>
        <comments_fr>En jouant avec scatterplot3d, il est possible d'obtenir un diagramme en baton en 3D. Le truc est d'utiliser type=&quot;h&quot; et lwd=5 pour une ligne solide ressemblant à une barre.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
References :
&lt;br/&gt;Ligges, U., and Maechler, M. (2003): Scatterplot3d - an R Package for Visualizing Multivariate Data. Journal of Statistical Software 8(11), 1-20. http://www.jstatsoft.org/
</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>40.057142857144</notemoy>
        <nbNote>35</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>117</id>
        <titre>Spinogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Spinogramme</titre_fr>
        <comments>Spinograms are an extension of histograms.
&lt;br/&gt;
References :
&lt;p&gt;
Hummel, J. (1996), Linked bar charts: Analysing categorical data graphically.
&lt;EM&gt;Computational Statistics&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;11&lt;/B&gt;, 23&amp;ndash;33.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hofmann, H., Theus, M. (2005), &lt;EM&gt;Interactive graphics for visualizing
conditional distributions&lt;/EM&gt;, Unpublished Manuscript.
&lt;/p&gt;</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les spinogrammes sont des extensions d'histogrammes.
&lt;br/&gt;
References :
&lt;p&gt;
Hummel, J. (1996), Linked bar charts: Analysing categorical data graphically.
&lt;EM&gt;Computational Statistics&lt;/EM&gt;, &lt;B&gt;11&lt;/B&gt;, 23&amp;ndash;33.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hofmann, H., Theus, M. (2005), &lt;EM&gt;Interactive graphics for visualizing
conditional distributions&lt;/EM&gt;, Unpublished Manuscript.
&lt;/p&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>14.6250625</notemoy>
        <nbNote>16</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>118</id>
        <titre>Three dimensional plotting</titre>
        <titre_fr>graphique 3d</titre_fr>
        <comments>Three dimensional plotting of points. Produces a nice-looking 3D scatterplot with greying out of further points givin a visual depth cue. Example with bunny data.</comments>
        <notemoy>69.963063026942</notemoy>
        <nbNote>247</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>119</id>
        <titre>Extended Sieve Plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Extended Sieve Plots</titre_fr>
        <comments>(Extended) sieve displays for n-way contingency tables: plots rectangles with areas proportional to the expected cell frequencies and filled with a number of squares equal to the observed frequencies. Thus, the densities visualize the deviations of the observed from the expected values.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
H. Riedwyl &amp;amp; M. Schüpbach (1994),
Parquet diagram to plot contingency tables.
In F. Faulbaum (ed.),

&lt;EM&gt;Softstat '93: Advances in Statistical Software&lt;/EM&gt;, 293&amp;ndash;299.
Gustav Fischer, New York.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
M. Friendly (2000),
Visualizing Categorical Data,
SAS Institute, Cary, NC.
&lt;/p&gt;


</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les rectangles ont l'aire proportionnelle à la valeur attendue et sont remplis par autant de carré que l'effectif observé. Ainsi, les densités de remplissage permet d'apprécier les écarts par rapports aux valeurs attendues.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
H. Riedwyl &amp;amp; M. Schüpbach (1994),
Parquet diagram to plot contingency tables.
In F. Faulbaum (ed.),

&lt;EM&gt;Softstat '93: Advances in Statistical Software&lt;/EM&gt;, 293&amp;ndash;299.
Gustav Fischer, New York.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
M. Friendly (2000),
Visualizing Categorical Data,
SAS Institute, Cary, NC.
&lt;/p&gt;
</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>72.142857142857</notemoy>
        <nbNote>7</nbNote>
        <example>sieve</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>120</id>
        <titre>Conditionnal Density Plots</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphique de densité conditionné</titre_fr>
        <comments>The plot describes how the distribution of a categorical variable y changes over a numerical variable x.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References :&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hofmann, H., Theus, M. (2005), &lt;EM&gt;Interactive graphics for visualizing
conditional distributions&lt;/EM&gt;, Unpublished Manuscript.

&lt;/p&gt;


</comments>
        <comments_fr>Le graphique montre l'évolution de la distribution d'une variable catégorielle selon une variable quantitative.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
References :&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hofmann, H., Theus, M. (2005), &lt;EM&gt;Interactive graphics for visualizing
conditional distributions&lt;/EM&gt;, Unpublished Manuscript.

&lt;/p&gt;
</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>48.944444444445</notemoy>
        <nbNote>18</nbNote>
        <example>cd_plot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>121</id>
        <titre>Circular density estimate</titre>
        <titre_fr>Estimation de densité circulaire</titre_fr>
        <comments>Circular density estimate</comments>
        <notemoy>67.384615384615</notemoy>
        <nbNote>13</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>122</id>
        <titre>Walter and Lieth climatic diagram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Diagram climatique de Walter and Lieth</titre_fr>
        <comments>Plot of a Walter &amp; Lieth climatic diagram of a station. &lt;br/&gt;
A good explanation on climatic diagram can be found 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zoolex.org/walter.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Trace un diagramme climatique de Walter &amp; Leith.&lt;br/&gt;
Une bonne introduction aux 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zoolex.org/walter.html&quot;&gt;diagrammes climatiques&lt;/a&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>65.499999999999</notemoy>
        <nbNote>42</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>123</id>
        <titre>Wind rose diagram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Wind rose diagram</titre_fr>
        <notemoy>69.048076923075</notemoy>
        <nbNote>104</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>124</id>
        <titre>Effect plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>Graphique d'effets</titre_fr>
        <comments>Effect display&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;

References : &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fox, J. (1987)
Effect displays for generalized linear models.
&lt;EM&gt;Sociological Methodology&lt;/EM&gt;
&lt;B&gt;17&lt;/B&gt;, 347&amp;ndash;361.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fox, J. (2003)
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstatsoft.org/counter.php?id=75&amp;amp;url=v08/i15/effect-displays-revised.pdf&amp;amp;ct=1&quot;&gt;Effect displays in R for generalised linear models&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;EM&gt;Journal of Statistical Software&lt;/EM&gt;

&lt;B&gt;8:15&lt;/B&gt;, 1&amp;ndash;27
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hastie, T. J. (1992)
Generalized additive models.
In Chambers, J. M., and Hastie, T. J. (eds.)
&lt;EM&gt;Statistical Models in S&lt;/EM&gt;, Wadsworth.
&lt;/p&gt;</comments>
        <comments_fr>Graphique d'effets&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
References : &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fox, J. (1987)
Effect displays for generalized linear models.
&lt;EM&gt;Sociological Methodology&lt;/EM&gt;
&lt;B&gt;17&lt;/B&gt;, 347&amp;ndash;361.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fox, J. (2003)
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstatsoft.org/counter.php?id=75&amp;amp;url=v08/i15/effect-displays-revised.pdf&amp;amp;ct=1&quot;&gt;Effect displays in R for generalised linear models&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;EM&gt;Journal of Statistical Software&lt;/EM&gt;

&lt;B&gt;8:15&lt;/B&gt;, 1&amp;ndash;27
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hastie, T. J. (1992)
Generalized additive models.
In Chambers, J. M., and Hastie, T. J. (eds.)
&lt;EM&gt;Statistical Models in S&lt;/EM&gt;, Wadsworth.
&lt;/p&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>63.869565217391</notemoy>
        <nbNote>23</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>125</id>
        <titre>Empirical Cumulative Distribution Function</titre>
        <titre_fr>Fonction de répartition empirique</titre_fr>
        <comments>Empirical Cumulative Distribution Function for a random sample of size 30 fo the standard normal distribution. The ecdf is overlayed with the theorical distribution function.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Fonction de répartition empirique pour un échantillon de taille 30 de la loi normale standard. La répartition théorique est ajoutée sur le même graphique. </comments_fr>
        <notemoy>22.315158738094</notemoy>
        <nbNote>126</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>126</id>
        <titre>Cumulative histogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>Histogramme cumulé</titre_fr>
        <comments>from : &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.itl.nist.gov/div898/handbook/eda/section3/histogra.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;The cumulative histogram is a variation of the histogram in which the vertical axis gives not just the counts for a single bin, but rather gives the counts for that bin plus all bins for smaller values of the response variable&lt;/font&gt;.</comments>
        <comments_fr>D'après &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.itl.nist.gov/div898/handbook/eda/section3/histogra.htm&quot;&gt;cette page&lt;/a&gt; :
&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;The cumulative histogram is a variation of the histogram in which the vertical axis gives not just the counts for a single bin, but rather gives the counts for that bin plus all bins for smaller values of the response variable&lt;/font&gt;.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>36.333333333334</notemoy>
        <nbNote>57</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>127</id>
        <titre>QQ plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>QQ plot</titre_fr>
        <comments>Quantile-Quantile plot for precip data against normal distribution. The added line passes by the first and third quartiles of data and normal distribution (quartiles are also located with big red dots)</comments>
        <comments_fr>QQplot pour les données precip contre la distribution gausienne. La ligne ajoutée joint les premier et troisième quartiles, visualisés par les points rouges.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>51.725</notemoy>
        <nbNote>80</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>400</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>128</id>
        <titre>quiver episode 2</titre>
        <titre_fr>quiver episode 2</titre_fr>
        <comments>This is a sequel of plot &lt;a href=&quot;RGraphGallery.php?graph=80&quot;&gt;80&lt;/a&gt; by B.D. Ripley and R. Hankin. Here quiver is much closer to its &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathworks.com/access/helpdesk/help/techdoc/ref/quiver.html&quot;&gt;matlab definition&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br/&gt;
We used argument plot.axes of filled.contour to add gray contour lines and arrows inside a filled.contour plot. </comments>
        <comments_fr>La suite du graph &lt;a href=&quot;RGraphGallery_fr.php?graph=80&quot;&gt;80&lt;/a&gt; de B.D. Ripley et R. Hankin. Ici quiver est plus proche de son &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathworks.com/access/helpdesk/help/techdoc/ref/quiver.html&quot;&gt;utilisation dans matlab&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br/&gt;
Le truc est d'utilisser l'argument plot.axes de filled.contour pour rajouter aux couleurs les lignes de niveaux en gris et les fleches à l'intérieur du graphique filled.contour.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>16.500000000002</notemoy>
        <nbNote>204</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>129</id>
        <titre>Thermometers</titre>
        <titre_fr>Thermometres</titre_fr>
        <comments>?</comments>
        <comments_fr>?</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>28.75</notemoy>
        <nbNote>8</nbNote>
        <example>symbols</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>130</id>
        <titre>Partitions of a qda classification</titre>
        <titre_fr>Partitions d'une analyse discriminante quadratique</titre_fr>
        <comments>Provides a multiple figure array which shows the classification of observations based on classification methods (e.g. lda, qda) for every combination of two variables. Moreover, the classification borders are displayed and the apparent error rates are given in each title.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Une matrice de nuages de points montrant les partitions d'une analyse discriminante (ici quadratique (lda)) pour chaque combinaison de deux variables. Les limites de la discrimination sont montrés et les taux d'erreur apparents sont affichés dans les titres.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>67.266666666666</notemoy>
        <nbNote>15</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>131</id>
        <titre>Self Organizing Maps</titre>
        <titre_fr>Carte de Kohonen</titre_fr>
        <comments>shardsplot corresponds to the representation method suggested by Cottrell and de Bodt (1996) for Kohonen Self-Organizing Maps. &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Reference :
&lt;br/&gt;
Cottrell, M., and de Bodt, E. (1996).
A Kohonen Map Representation to Avoid Misleading Interpretations.
&lt;EM&gt;Proceedings of the European Symposium on Atrificial Neural Networks&lt;/EM&gt;, D-Facto, pp. 103&amp;ndash;110.</comments>
        <comments_fr>shardplot correspond à la représentation suggérée par Cottrell et de Bodt (1996) pour les carte auto organisatrices de Kohonen.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Reference :
&lt;br/&gt;
Cottrell, M., and de Bodt, E. (1996).
A Kohonen Map Representation to Avoid Misleading Interpretations.
&lt;EM&gt;Proceedings of the European Symposium on Atrificial Neural Networks&lt;/EM&gt;, D-Facto, pp. 103&amp;ndash;110.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>60.377906976742</notemoy>
        <nbNote>172</nbNote>
        <example>shardsplot</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>132</id>
        <titre>SOM representatives star plot</titre>
        <titre_fr>diagramme en etoile des représentants d'une carte de Kohonen</titre_fr>
        <comments>Star plot of the representatives of a batch Self Organizing map (SOM) applied on crabs data.
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Kohonen, T. (1995) &lt;EM&gt;Self-Organizing Maps.&lt;/EM&gt; Springer-Verlag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Ripley, B. D. (1996)
&lt;EM&gt;Pattern Recognition and Neural Networks.&lt;/EM&gt; Cambridge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Venables, W. N. and Ripley, B. D. (2002)
&lt;EM&gt;Modern Applied Statistics with S.&lt;/EM&gt; Fourth edition.  Springer.
&lt;/p&gt;</comments>
        <comments_fr>Diagramme en etoile des représentants d'une carte auto organisatrice de Kohonen sur les données crabs.
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Kohonen, T. (1995) &lt;EM&gt;Self-Organizing Maps.&lt;/EM&gt; Springer-Verlag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Ripley, B. D. (1996)
&lt;EM&gt;Pattern Recognition and Neural Networks.&lt;/EM&gt; Cambridge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Venables, W. N. and Ripley, B. D. (2002)
&lt;EM&gt;Modern Applied Statistics with S.&lt;/EM&gt; Fourth edition.  Springer.
&lt;/p&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>0.61286472148542</notemoy>
        <nbNote>1508</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>133</id>
        <titre>Assignments of a SOM</titre>
        <titre_fr>Affectations d'une carte de Kohonen</titre_fr>
        <comments>This plot shows the points from crabs dataset assigned by a SOM (Self Organizing Map).
The points are placed randomly in the circle thay belong.
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Kohonen, T. (1995) &lt;EM&gt;Self-Organizing Maps.&lt;/EM&gt; Springer-Verlag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Ripley, B. D. (1996)
&lt;EM&gt;Pattern Recognition and Neural Networks.&lt;/EM&gt; Cambridge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Venables, W. N. and Ripley, B. D. (2002)
&lt;EM&gt;Modern Applied Statistics with S.&lt;/EM&gt; Fourth edition.  Springer.
&lt;/p&gt; </comments>
        <comments_fr>Ce graphique montre les points du jeu de données carbs affectés par une carte de Kohonen. Chaque point est placé au hasard dans son cercle.
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Kohonen, T. (1995) &lt;EM&gt;Self-Organizing Maps.&lt;/EM&gt; Springer-Verlag.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Ripley, B. D. (1996)
&lt;EM&gt;Pattern Recognition and Neural Networks.&lt;/EM&gt; Cambridge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Venables, W. N. and Ripley, B. D. (2002)
&lt;EM&gt;Modern Applied Statistics with S.&lt;/EM&gt; Fourth edition.  Springer.
&lt;/p&gt;</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>52.133333333334</notemoy>
        <nbNote>30</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>134</id>
        <titre>teapot</titre>
        <titre_fr>théière</titre_fr>
        <comments>The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sjbaker.org/teapot&quot;&gt;teapot&lt;/a&gt; is a common example of 3d graphics. This graph uses R to
transform and display the teapot as viewed from any angle.  It also
demonstrates plotting a solid object comprised of 3d patches on a 2d
graph.</comments>
        <comments_fr>La &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sjbaker.org/teapot/&quot;&gt;théière&lt;/a&gt; est un exemple courant de graphique 3d. Ce graph utilise R pour transformer et montrer une théière à différents points de vue. Il montre aussi comment tracer un objet solide 3d sur un graphique 2d.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>12.704286400267</notemoy>
        <nbNote>243</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>135</id>
        <titre>teapot 2</titre>
        <titre_fr>théière 2</titre_fr>
        <comments>The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sjbaker.org/teapot&quot;&gt;teapot&lt;/a&gt; is a common example of 3d graphics. This graph uses R to transform and display the teapot as viewed from any angle. It also demonstrates plotting a solid object comprised of 3d patches on a 2d graph.</comments>
        <comments_fr>La théière est un exemple courant de graphique 3d. Ce graph utilise R pour transformer et montrer une théière à différents points de vue. Il montre aussi comment tracer un objet solide 3d sur un graphique 2d.</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>75.664705882353</notemoy>
        <nbNote>170</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>136</id>
        <titre>back to back histogram</titre>
        <titre_fr>back to back histogram</titre_fr>
        <comments>The two histogram are plotted back to each other.</comments>
        <comments_fr>Les deux histogrammes sont affichés face à face</comments_fr>
        <notemoy>38.14101208955</notemoy>
        <nbNote>201</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>450</px_w>
        <px_h>450</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>137</id>
        <titre>Correlation Matrix</titre>
        <titre_fr>Matrice de Corrélation</titre_fr>
        <comments>Visualization of a Correlation Matrix. On top the (absolute) value of the correlation plus the result of the cor.test as stars. On botttom, the bivariate scatterplots, with a fitted line</comments>
        <notemoy>57.86896551724</notemoy>
        <nbNote>145</nbNote>
        <example>pairs</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>500</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>138</id>
        <titre>See wave</titre>
        <comments>This is a graphical representation of a tree cricket calling song (Oecanthus pellucens).
An oscillogram (amplitude vs time) is associated to a spectrogram (time vs frequency vs amplitude).
Different colour palettes can be applied to the spectrogram.
</comments>
        <notemoy>21.139072847682</notemoy>
        <nbNote>151</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>139</id>
        <titre>Scatterplots with smoothed densities color representation</titre>
        <comments>smoothScatter produces a smoothed color density representation
     of the scatterplot, obtained through a kernel density estimate.
     densCols produces a vector containing colors which encode the
     local densities at each point in a scatterplot.</comments>
        <notemoy>77.109677419354</notemoy>
        <nbNote>155</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>400</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>140</id>
        <titre>Seasonal temperature</titre>
        <comments>Seasonal temperature normals for Vancouver, BC, Canada, between 1975 and 2004, made with plot.seas.temp. The boxplots are from the daily mean values and the thick vertical lines diurnal variability as derived from the median of the daily maximum and minimum temperatures. In this case the whiskers of the boxplots are greater than the diurnal temperature range in the winter (on the order of the 25-75 percentiles) and of the same order of magnitude in the summer (on the order of the 5-95 percentiles).</comments>
        <notemoy>28.329581993573</notemoy>
        <nbNote>311</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>569</px_w>
        <px_h>453</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>141</id>
        <titre>Seasonal precipitation</titre>
        <comments>Seasonal precipitation in Vancouver, BC, Canada, between 1975 and 2004, created from image.seas.sum. The upper-left frame is the normalized sum of precipitation in 11-day groups for the years of data, which sum to the upper-right frame (same as annual precipitation totals); the lower-left frame is sorted vertically to make the sample quantiles and is contoured; the lower-right frame is the sums of the sample quantiles; the vertical line indicates the median of the annual sums, and the horizontal line represents the seasonal 'normal' that has the same annual amount.</comments>
        <notemoy>1.9950203712088</notemoy>
        <nbNote>4418</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>534</px_w>
        <px_h>525</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>142</id>
        <titre>disconnected sets for two-way classification</titre>
        <comments>Find and plot disconnected sets and hence test for estimability in a 
two-way cell-means model without interaction.</comments>
        <notemoy>0.47372074882981</notemoy>
        <nbNote>5128</nbNote>
        <example>plot.connectedness</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>143</id>
        <titre>hexbin pie</titre>
        <titre_fr>hexbin pie</titre_fr>
        <comments>This plotting function can be used to visualize a categorical variable
against a pair of continuous variables (x,y). The original data on the
x,y plane are divided into hexagonal bins with the aid of
biocunductor's hexbin package. The data falling into the same bin are
then visualized by small piecharts, whose area is proportional to the
amount of points in the bin. This structure makes it easy to get a
visual impression of the separation of the classes in the x,y plane.
In order to get a smoother visualization, the area of the piechart
circles is proportional to the  bin counts only in the middle of the
count range. The piecharts in the bins with the highest 5% of counts
are all scaled to the maximum radius (fitting into the hexagon), and
in order to be able to compare these cases, the counts are added as
text in the middle of the corresponding bins. On the other hand
piecharts with very low counts, are rounded up to 20% of the maximum
radius (otherwise one could not see the coulours).
The colours of the categories, the hexagonal grid, and the outline of
the piecharts, and the extreme counts can be set at function call,
with sensible defaults. The latter three can also be turned out by
specifying NA. </comments>
        <notemoy>0.31542519372183</notemoy>
        <nbNote>20132</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>700</px_w>
        <px_h>700</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>144</id>
        <titre>Multicolor text in title</titre>
        <comments>This uses the &lt;a href=&quot;http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/R/library/grDevices/html/plotmath.html&quot;&gt;phantom&lt;/a&gt; function to create a multicolored title. 

This is based on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://stat.ethz.ch/pipermail/r-help/2009-January/185695.html&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; on r-help and was also discussed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.revolution-computing.com/2009/01/multicolor-text-in-r.html&quot;&gt;revolutions&lt;/a&gt; blog</comments>
        <notemoy>100</notemoy>
        <nbNote>1</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>500</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>145</id>
        <titre>Image profiles</titre>
        <comments>&lt;p&gt;These are two scripts which I wrote because I did not find any tool, which is able to produce these kinds of graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For marketing purposes you need so called profile diagrammes and image profiles.
Both types of diagrammes have to show the position of each object, which can be a brand, an enterprise, a person or whatsoever in comparison to other objects.
The graph is a kind of traditional XY-graph rotated 90 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profile diagrammes are used in marketing to show the position of research objects. The research criterea or items are shown on the y-axis and the values on the x-axis.
Image Profiles work quite similar. They compare objects using items which are measured in so called pair of opposites.
The data mostly comes from questionaires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These scripts are non-interactive versions of a originally interactive R-script just to demonstrate the idea of the script.
You will find a lot of comments within the script explaining the way they work.
The interactive scripts are more flexible, because they read the data from csv-files and ask, whether the output should be a file or on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interactive scripts hve been developed as part of a marketing book. The scripts are available free on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reymann.eu&quot;&gt;the website&lt;/a&gt;
Look for &quot;Wettbewerbsanalysen&quot; and the download files in the sections of the chapters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book will be available in the bookshops starting in march 2009:
Author: Reymann, Detlev
Title: Wettbewerbsanalysen für kleine und mittlere Unternehmen (KMUs) - Theoretische Grundlagen und praktische Anwendung am Beispiel gartenbaulicher Betriebe
Note: ISBN: 978-3-00-027013-0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interactive scripts are available in german only in the moment but if there is interest, I will produce english versions as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scripting is far away from being perfect, especially regarding the construction of the caption.
Hints on improving the script from &quot;R-professionals&quot; are very welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</comments>
        <notemoy>65</notemoy>
        <nbNote>2</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>550</px_w>
        <px_h>800</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>146</id>
        <titre>multipanel geographic Lattice plot</titre>
        <comments>Plot showing the geographic distribution of murder rates (1976) 
for the United States of America. It is created by dividing the 
murder rates into partially overlapping intervals, and colouring the 
corresponding states using Lattice graphics. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2288400&quot;&gt;Cleveland and McGill (1984) &lt;/a&gt; for alternative 
ways to present the same information.</comments>
        <notemoy>18</notemoy>
        <nbNote>5</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>800</px_w>
        <px_h>600</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>147</id>
        <titre>Correlation Ellipses</titre>
        <comments>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;corrgram&lt;/code&gt; function produces a graphical display of a correlation matrix, called a correlogram. The cells of the matrix can be shaded or colored to show the correlation value. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/corrgram/index.html&quot;&gt;corrgram&lt;/a&gt; package&lt;/p&gt;</comments>
        <notemoy>45.5</notemoy>
        <nbNote>2</nbNote>
        <example>corrgram</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>800</px_w>
        <px_h>800</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>148</id>
        <titre>Correlograms</titre>
        <comments>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;corrgram&lt;/code&gt; function produces a graphical display of a correlation matrix, called a correlogram. The cells of the matrix can be shaded or colored to show the correlation value. &lt;/p&gt;

See the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/corrgram/index.html&quot;&gt;corrgram&lt;/a&gt; package</comments>
        <notemoy>30</notemoy>
        <nbNote>2</nbNote>
        <example>corrgram</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>800</px_w>
        <px_h>800</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>149</id>
        <titre>Correlation matrix ellipses</titre>
        <comments>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;plotcorr&lt;/code&gt; function plots a correlation matrix using ellipse-shaped glyphs for each entry. The ellipse represents a level curve of the density of a bivariate normal with the matching correlation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murdoch, D.J. and Chow, E.D. (1996). A graphical display of large correlation matrices. The American Statistician 50, 178-180.&lt;/a&gt;</comments>
        <notemoy>62.857142857143</notemoy>
        <nbNote>7</nbNote>
        <example>plotcorr</example>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>700</px_w>
        <px_h>700</px_h>
    </graph>
    <graph>
        <id>150</id>
        <titre>steep decline in market capitalization</titre>
        <comments>&lt;p&gt;This is an alternative version of the graph used by the financial times to represent steep decline in market capitalization. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ftalphaville.ft.com/blog/2009/01/21/51474/bank-chart-du-jour/&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://alphaville.ftdata.co.uk/lib/inc/getfile/4156.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://ftalphaville.ft.com/blog/2009/01/21/51474/bank-chart-du-jour/&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.revolution-computing.com/2009/02/graphic-literacy-improving.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the full story.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This alternative is using a simple lattice &lt;code&gt;dotplot&lt;/code&gt; to present the information. See the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bm2.genes.nig.ac.jp/RGM2/R_current/library/lattice/man/xyplot.html&quot;&gt;graphical manuals&lt;/a&gt; for other dotplot examples&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also another alternative&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.portfolio.com/views/blogs/market-movers/2009/01/21/bank-capitalization-chart-of-the-day?tid=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.portfolio.com/images/feeds/blogs/bankchart2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
</comments>
        <notemoy>42.5</notemoy>
        <nbNote>4</nbNote>
        <nbKeywords>0</nbKeywords>
        <boolForum>0</boolForum>
        <px_w>600</px_w>
        <px_h>800</px_h>
    </graph>
</addictedtor>

